<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="https://luispuerto.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://luispuerto.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-03-12T21:31:46+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://luispuerto.net/</id>

  
    <title type="html">Luis Puerto’s Blog</title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Forestry | Research | GIS | Remote Sensing</subtitle>
  

  
    <author>
        <name>Luis Puerto</name>
      
      
    </author>
  

  
  

  

  
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">No message, no connection in LinkedIn</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/21/no-message-no-connection-in-linkedin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No message, no connection in LinkedIn" />
      <published>2019-02-21T21:25:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-21T21:25:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/21/no-message-no-connection-in-linkedin</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/21/no-message-no-connection-in-linkedin/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2019/linkedin-logo-header.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        

        &lt;p&gt;I think this is something that almost anyone with a LinkedIn account has suffered or happened to them… an invitation to connect that comes out of the blue from someone you don’t know. No message, or just the standard message, no explanation, nothing… just an invitation in your LinkedIn inbox from someone, usually with a happy face —maybe a fake one— that perhaps is in a similar field as yours —or not— and they live close to you —or they don’t. &lt;strong&gt;I hate it&lt;/strong&gt;, because I need to figure out who this person is and what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are they? Are they bots? Are they mining personal information? Are they just people that can figure out how social interactions should work? Did they click in my profile by mistake? What is going on here? A really don’t understand :confused:.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/lion-funny.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Simply no words
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/lion-funny.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;a funny lion&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Simply no words

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok… after a brief search on internet about the topic, now I understand… They are &lt;a href=&quot;http://greenbuzzagency.com/what-is-a-lion-on-linkedin-2/&quot;&gt;LIONs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; —&lt;em&gt;LinkedIn Open Networkers&lt;/em&gt;— in other words they are people which only goal is to grow their LinkedIn’s network —to huge numbers— so it’s easier for them to connect to other people &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; interesting for them in the future and appear in more people’s searches. LinkedIn only allow you to connect to other people when you are up to 3 degrees of separation from that person and the same for searchers, you only show up when you are up to 3 degrees of separation away. So when you have a huge network you have more probability to be at 3 or less degrees of separation those contact you really want to connect with. You can find longest explanation &lt;a href=&quot;https://topdogsocialmedia.com/why-i-dont-connect-with-lions-on-linkedin/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/Why-do-you-receive-random-LinkedIn-invitations&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t get me wrong. I’m nothing special&lt;/strong&gt;, just a professional looking for opportunities and someone who is, of course, really glad to meet and connect with other people. I think LinkedIn could be a great place to do it. The problem is that you just don’t poke, or connect, people randomly without knowing anything about them, without telling them why do you want to know more about them and/or telling a little bit about you. If you sent me a message —in or &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;out LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;— telling me why you want to connect with me —just a line, or a couple if you want— then I will be more than happy to connect with you. On the condition that you have a real and meaningful reason you want to connect. If you send me a standard message or you tell me that you &lt;em&gt;just want to connect&lt;/em&gt;, it has the same effect as it you tell me nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you imagine that you are in a bar, a conference or just in the street and you decide to give your business card to random people and passersby? With no reason at all? Telling to all of them the same artificial phrase without trying to learn anything about them. Would you take their card? Would you keep it? No I guess no, because it doesn’t have any sense unless you are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_billboard&quot;&gt;human billboard&lt;/a&gt; and giving handouts to everyone without any filter, which most probably will end up in the garbage. Aren’t you a seasoned professional that you really want to stand out other the rest? Don’t you really want to look professional?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/LinkedIn-connection-note.png&quot; title=&quot;C’mon guys!!!! The option to “add a note” to that connection request is just there
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/LinkedIn-connection-note.png&quot; alt=&quot;LinkedIn connect with add a note button&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      C’mon guys!!!! The option to “add a note” to that connection request is just there

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, just imagine for a second. You are in the same bar, conference or just in the street (in some event or something) and someone approach you, introduce himself, tell you that knows you from XYZ, and they would love to know more about your work and they hand you their card. I’m sure your perspective changes a lot about that person and you are provably going to remember them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-right&quot; style=&quot;width: 40%&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/LInkedIn-recomendations.png&quot; title=&quot;This is the problem, the LinkedIn recommendations panel
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/LInkedIn-recomendations.png&quot; alt=&quot;LinkedIn recommendations&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      This is the problem, the LinkedIn recommendations panel

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem seems to be related to the &lt;em&gt;Recommended for you&lt;/em&gt; panel on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/mynetwork/?lipi=urn%3Ali%3Apage%3Ad_flagship3_people%3BI1%2BtgQBtQf%2BCV%2BK1F7uGrA%3D%3D&quot;&gt;My Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; section. If you click on one of those &lt;em&gt;connect&lt;/em&gt; buttons, it seems that a direct invitation to connect is sent to that profile, without asking you if you want to add a note —yes please! I’m wondering now if this &lt;em&gt;isn’t a bug, but a feature&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, does Microsoft want you to have as much connections as possible? What for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t care what are the current LinkedIn dynamics, or if they have changed since &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/06/14/business/dealbook/microsoft-to-buy-linkedin-for-26-2-billion.html&quot;&gt;Microsoft has bought it&lt;/a&gt;. In my opinion it’s plainly wrong to send invitations to connect with people you don’t know out of the blue and without any message. Instead of just clicking on that connect button in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/mynetwork/?lipi=urn%3Ali%3Apage%3Ad_flagship3_people%3BI1%2BtgQBtQf%2BCV%2BK1F7uGrA%3D%3D&quot;&gt;My Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; section, you can check the LinkedIn’s profile of the person is suggested to you and in their profile you can click on connect —if you consider the person is worth to connect with— and add a note to your invitation to connect —YAY! :thumbsup:. Even if I know you beforehand, in real life or just because we’ve been exchanging emails —or whatever— you should add a note to refresh my memory or send a message outside of LinkedIn. Memories fail! :thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/4-reasons-accept-every-random-linkedin-invitation-john-buckley/&quot;&gt;this guy states&lt;/a&gt;, if you don’t add a message to your invitation you are showing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That you are &lt;strong&gt;indistinguishable&lt;/strong&gt; of all the other invitations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are &lt;strong&gt;disingenuous&lt;/strong&gt;, that I’m going to include you in my network just because you send me an invitation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You lack of &lt;strong&gt;creativity&lt;/strong&gt; and you are &lt;strong&gt;lazy&lt;/strong&gt; since you decided not to even check my profile —and contact me from there, either in LinkedIn using a note to your invitation or using my contact info— and if you have done so, you decided explicitly not to write a note :thumbsdown:. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is worsen by LinkedIn, since you can’t ask to someone that is asking you to connect with exactly why they want to connect with you, since that is a &lt;em&gt;premium&lt;/em&gt; :money_mouth_face: feature to send messages to people outside your network. So people don’t want to pay, which is normal with that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/comm/premium/products?family=jss&amp;amp;trk=pre_hub_b_upgrade&quot;&gt;prices&lt;/a&gt;, and just try to connect with others in the free tier. Perhaps LinkedIn should allow to at least reply to those invitations with a message asking for more info.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that sending a message, check the profile or research a little bit sometimes is a lot of effort, but I really think it’s worth it. I have this web, where you can find my &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;contact information&lt;/a&gt; and contact me in several different ways. I also have my contact information in my LinkedIn profile. There is no excuse to send me a message telling me who you are and why are you interested in me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center xx-large&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NO MORE RANDOM INVITATIONS, please!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To be honest, and after giving it a thought, I don’t think they are even that, because I bet an arm that most of them don’t know what a LION is. I didn’t know until I wrote this piece and I doubt most people in LinkedIn know about that. They just connect because they know they are going to get something on the long run or just because LinkedIn is suggesting them to do so. They just click in connect under your profile. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/21/no-message-no-connection-in-linkedin/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;No message, no connection in LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="LinkedIn" />
      
        <category term="social media" />
      
        <category term="networking" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I think this is something that almost anyone with a LinkedIn account has suffered or happened to them… an invitation to connect that comes out of the blue from someone you don’t know. No message, or just the standard message, no explanation, nothing… just an invitation in your LinkedIn inbox from someone, usually with a happy face —maybe a fake one— that perhaps is in a similar field as yours —or not— and they live close to you —or they don’t. I hate it, because I need to figure out who this person is and what they want.</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2019/linkedin-logo-header.png" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Discovering Hypothes.is</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/10/discovering-hypothesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discovering Hypothes.is" />
      <published>2019-02-10T13:15:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-10T13:15:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/10/discovering-hypothesis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/10/discovering-hypothesis/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2019/HypothesisBannerGoogleForms.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        

        &lt;p&gt;I just discovered &lt;a href=&quot;https://hypothes.is/&quot;&gt;Hypothes.is&lt;/a&gt; which is a service to annotate and highlight articles, posts, pdfs or whatever text you want and find all over the web and in any site. In their own words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Hypothesis Project is a new effort to implement an old idea: A conversation layer over the entire web that works everywhere, without needing implementation by any underlying site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All their tools are open source and free, and they can be checked &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.hypothes.is/developers/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, which make the services even more attractive to me. They’re also a &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.hypothes.is/about/&quot;&gt;non-profict&lt;/a&gt; organization, if you are wondering if there any comercial interest in the tools they’re developing. In addition, they provide &lt;a href=&quot;https://outline.com&quot;&gt;outline.com&lt;/a&gt;, which is similar to hypothes.is but transforming the article in a readable version without all the clutter websites usually have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can start using them right away, &lt;a href=&quot;https://hypothes.is/signup&quot;&gt;creating yourself an account in hypothes.is&lt;/a&gt; and firing up either hypothesi.is or outline in any web you want using the lightweight &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.hypothes.is/start/&quot;&gt;bookmarklets&lt;/a&gt; to share your annotations and highlights with others. You can find a outline bookmarklet below. Please note… when you are highlighting and annotating in outline, you are just annotating there. Your comments aren’t going to be share in the main article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-left&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 50%&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/HypotheisisHighlight.png&quot; title=&quot;hypothes.is highlighting and annotation tool
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/HypotheisisHighlight.png&quot; alt=&quot;hypothes.is highlighting and annotation tool&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      hypothes.is highlighting and annotation tool

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool is really easy to use, you just click in the bookmarklet and small buttons in the side pops up.  Then, you just select text and a pop up will ask you if you want to highlight or annotate. You can also view the comments, notes and highlights from others users of the tool, which is even more interesting, and you can also comment in those annotation and reply to other annotations. Finally, it seems that it’s possible to create groups, so you can share your notes with others privately or publicly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the image below, outline do exactly the same, but in a clean interface that helps you to read the article without distractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/HypothesisOutline.png&quot; title=&quot;outline interface with hypothes.is highlights
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2019/HypothesisOutline.png&quot; alt=&quot;outline interface with hypothes.is highlights&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      outline interface with hypothes.is highlights

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web developers can also &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.hypothes.is/help/embedding-hypothesis-in-websites-and-platforms/&quot;&gt;implement this tool in their webs&lt;/a&gt;, so when users select text the annotation and highlight tool pops up in a really &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;medium-like way&lt;/a&gt; without the need to trigger it using the bookmarklet. I was thinking to implement it in my site, and I even was toying with it in a branch, but I finally decided to leave you the option of using it or not through the bookmarklet. Mainly for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First of all. &lt;strong&gt;You choose&lt;/strong&gt;. I don’t want to impose anything into any one.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second of all. I think the implementation is &lt;em&gt;too intrusive&lt;/em&gt; to have it all the time there. You can implement it in two ways, classic or clean.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The classic way makes the sidebar always present through its  buttons and somehow interfered with the design of the site. Mostly on mobile.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The clean way doesn’t show you anything until you select text, but them you are missing some features such us: marks of where the annotations are, or the ability to turn the annotations on and off. This wouldn’t bee a problem if users can bring all the features triggering the bookmarklet, but it doesn’t work like that.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps in the future I will integrate it in someway if they improve how it blend with webs or if they for example develop something to transform the notes into comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the idea of being able to have a layer of notes and highlights all across the web. It’s a great idea. I hope that the idea evolved in a sort of organization like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Foundation&lt;/a&gt; and it becomes a standard all across the web. I really think it’s a great tool to share information with others, ever more if it’s related to &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.hypothes.is/research/&quot;&gt;research and science&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.hypothes.is/education/&quot;&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;.  I encourage you to use the tool and share your notes with others.&lt;/p&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/10/discovering-hypothesis/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Discovering Hypothes.is&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="research" />
      
        <category term="tools" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I just discovered Hypothes.is which is a service to annotate and highlight articles, posts, pdfs or whatever text you want and find all over the web and in any site. In their own words:</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2019/HypothesisBannerGoogleForms.png" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What have I been doing these last years?</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/03/what-Ive-been-doing-these-last-years/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What have I been doing these last years?" />
      <published>2019-02-03T19:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-03T19:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/03/what-Ive-been-doing-these-last-years</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/03/what-Ive-been-doing-these-last-years/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/existential-nihilism-header.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        

        &lt;p class=&quot;notice--danger&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning!&lt;/strong&gt; This is a very long post and it’s probably boring for your. &lt;u&gt;Read it at your &lt;b&gt;own risk&lt;/b&gt;!&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since some people has asked me this question once in a while, I thought it was going to be a good idea to write a &lt;em&gt;small&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:0&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; post about &lt;em&gt;what I’ve been doing these last years since I left Spain&lt;/em&gt;. I think I’m going to give it the shape of an &lt;em&gt;informal resume / curriculum&lt;/em&gt; where I’m going to talk, superficially, about each of the things I’ve been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I really want do differentiate between quality and quantity time. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quality_time&quot;&gt;Quality time&lt;/a&gt; for me has, more or less, the meaning everyone gives to it on the English language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality time&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;QT&lt;/strong&gt;) is an informal reference to time spent with close family, partners or friends that is in some way important, special, productive or profitable. It is time that is set aside for paying full and undivided attention to the person or matter at hand. It may also refer to time spent &lt;strong&gt;performing some favorite activity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would add that, for me, it isn’t only that but also time that I spend on myself… doing whatever I enjoy and I think it’s going to be positive for me, even if it’s in the long run. They are also those kind of activities that are really difficult to quantify, but they stand out for their quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, in my opinion there is the quantity time concept, of which I couldn’t find a formal definition, but I would define as all that other time that you can usually quantify —hours, days, weeks, months or years— doing something specific. Working, &lt;del&gt;learning&lt;/del&gt; getting a diploma&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, volunteering… This is usually the kind of things that people put in their curriculums because they can be undoubtedly quantified —they can be weighted— so other people usually can take them into account —and measure you in some way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center gigantic&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality vs. Quantity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the important question. What do you prefer to have? Quality or quantity in your life? It’s pretty clear that if you could, you would like to have both. However, you can’t always have both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also have to understand that since I learned about &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Optimistic &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nihilism&quot;&gt;Nihilism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;philosophy&lt;/em&gt;, I think this is the correct way to understand the universe. However, as they say in the video &lt;em&gt;please they it with a grain of salt &lt;del&gt;we&lt;/del&gt; I don’t know any more about human existence that you do&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MBRqu0YOH14&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;large&quot;&gt;If this is our one shot at life, there is no reason not to &lt;strong&gt;have fun and live as happy as possible&lt;/strong&gt;. Bonus points if you make the life of &lt;strong&gt;other people&lt;/strong&gt; better. More bonus points if you help build a &lt;strong&gt;Galactic Human Empire&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/existential-nihilism.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;It is like riding the bicycle of life, knowing that the road ends at an inevitable lethal fall, knowing that riding it on has no fundamental reason but you ride on, you ride on the road to enjoy the journey, to look around you and just feel like you’re the product of million of years of complexity, it’s like looking at the trees around you and saying, “Holy shit, I love this. This is freaking awesome.” Source: Quora
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/existential-nihilism.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Existential Nihilism&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;It is like riding the bicycle of life, knowing that the road ends at an inevitable lethal fall, knowing that riding it on has no fundamental reason but you ride on, you ride on the road to enjoy the journey, to look around you and just feel like you’re the product of million of years of complexity, it’s like looking at the trees around you and saying, “Holy shit, I love this. This is freaking awesome.”&lt;/em&gt; Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/TUtwbA&quot;&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quality-time&quot;&gt;Quality Time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enjoying-my-life&quot;&gt;Enjoying my life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is first and foremost important thing I’ve been doing, &lt;strong&gt;enjoying my life&lt;/strong&gt;, and I think &lt;strong&gt;you should too!&lt;/strong&gt; We are clearly here to enjoy our life, not to suffer. I’ve been doing all the things I explain in this post —and some others— and I’ve been enjoying them. No regrets. Perhaps some of the things haven’t been as productive, as good, or didn’t turn out as expected, however, in the end, all of them, have been positive because they’ve been part of this trip that is life, and I’ve learned from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discovering--developing-myself&quot;&gt;Discovering &amp;amp; developing myself&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things I’ve been doing have been really positive for my personal development, I’ve been discovering part of myself that I didn’t know till now and I’ve been even discovering parts of my personality that I didn’t know I have. All of these, help me to be a better person, better professional and be more productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning&quot;&gt;Learning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of that discovery and personal development are related to learning. Learning new skills, and learning that you can learn new skills. We are natural learners, but for some reason some people decide that they don’t want to learn anymore. They end up stuck in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;improving-my-english&quot;&gt;Improving my English&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this time I’ve been improving my English since I’ve been living in an international environment and I’ve tried to travel as much I could —and still try. I’ve been living for almost 5 years in Finland, where almost all the time in my daily life I have to use English for communicating with others. Before coming to Finland I was living 6 months in Sweden where the same happened. During the period we’ve been living in Finland we moved for 5 month to the west coast of the United States where my English had an incredible boost. I tried to speak with people as much as possible —without weird anyone out— and one my fondest memories is talking and discussing with our landlord and housemate for really long hours about the most diverse topics: politics, life, science, philosophy, Europe, America, forestry, ecology, life…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;learning-other-languages&quot;&gt;Learning other languages&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I live in Finland, I’ve been learning Finnish and I am able to speak a little bit. Not enough to maintain a normal and regular conversation for sure, but it has serve me well in a variety of situations when I’ve needed it. Learning Finnish, has been a really &lt;em&gt;interesting experience&lt;/em&gt;. It’s in different language family, so you usually have to start from scratch since you aren’t going to have any reference or resemblance with your mother tongue —unless you are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finno-Ugric_languages&quot;&gt;Estonian, Hungarian or part of the small Fino-Ugric family&lt;/a&gt;. In my particular case, my mother tongue is Spanish and pronunciation of Finnish isn’t a &lt;em&gt;pain in the tongue&lt;/em&gt;, more the other way around, but grammar is totally different and really difficult. Besides of what painful has been learn the little Finnish I speak, it’s been a really change of perspective on thinking. Languages are a way of thinking and Finnish is a really particular one, usually really concise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also leaned a little bit of Swedish while I lived in Sweden —which was much easier than Finnish— but I’ve almost forgotten all of it. I liked Swedish because it’s a really nice language to listen, really rhythmic and even sometimes, funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;coding--computer-skills&quot;&gt;Coding &amp;amp; computer skills&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these years I’ve been improving my computer stills a lot. I’ve been introducing to coding, and now I’m able to code in R, and I’m beginning to code in other languages as Rubi, CSS, HTML or Liquid. Proof of that is this website that I’ve little by little changing from the original template to what you see it now to adjust to my necessities. I’ve even add new functionalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been also learn to use Git, and I use it almost everyday to keep track of my work. Also, I’ve increase incredible the use of the shell and the command line, where I’ve also write scripts from time to time when I need them, either to analyze LiDAR data using Fusion —or any other software— or to fulfill my necessities in macOS or Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been learning about Linux too, since I have a couple of Raspberry Pis which I use for different tasks at home, like have a VPN server, or NAS, audio server, VPN router… or whatever it comes to my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reading&quot;&gt;Reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading is another way of learning about stuff, but usually in a more relaxing way —usually when you are close to go to bed. In the last years I’ve been able to reconcile with reading and I’ve been able to increase the number of books I’ve been reading little by little. Internet it’s great, but in my opinion sometimes, or most of the times, lacks the substance that books usually have. Returning to reading has improved my ability to concentrate, which was eroded by internet. In the last year, I as able to read read 7 books, but I’ve started the year strong and in the last month I read two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been increasing my readings and I plan to increase even more since little by little I find the internet more boring everyday. Perhaps, I’m getting old, or perhaps is it has lost its nobility. Don’t get me wrong, I still spend a lot of time reading on the internet and it’s still my primary source of fresh information. Nevertheless, I started to despise &lt;a href=&quot;/archive/tags/facebook/&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; —and all its ecosystem— and most of the other &lt;em&gt;social networks&lt;/em&gt;. I still use &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; quite a lot, and I’m a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; fan, but they lack features to create a really meaningful communication of ideas and it’s difficult to create quality content those platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-fifth-discipline&quot;&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of books I read these last years is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fifth_Discipline&quot;&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt;”, an all-time classic of organizational management, and in some regards much more, since it can lead to a different view of the world. I discovered The Fifth Discipline thanks to the CEO of the last organization I was working in Spain. I really think it’s a great book and of course an interesting way to see organizations and humans interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I begun to feel interest for management, organizational science and productivity also while I was in Spain. There I learned that you can have all the resources of the world to create or do whatever you want, but if you haven’t assembled a good and effective team, you aren’t going to succeed. Teams are made or people, not computers, office furniture, buildings, gadgets, or factories. Most managers doesn’t understand that people are the basic building blocks of their organization, so people is to what you have to play attention to. &lt;strong&gt;Humans aren’t a resource, but an investment&lt;/strong&gt;, that in the end will really pay off. Senge really understand this and explain it much better than me in his books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, what is The Fifth Discipline? &lt;strong&gt;System Thinking&lt;/strong&gt;, the ability of seeing the world in a systemic way. It integrated the other four: &lt;strong&gt;Personal mastery, Mental Models, Building a Shared Vision and Team Learning&lt;/strong&gt;. I don’t have the time here to explain any of them, and I really don’t think it’s the place. If you want to know more, I really recommend to read any of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge#Publications&quot;&gt;Senge’s books&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enjoying-my-life-with-the-person-i-love&quot;&gt;Enjoying my life with the person I love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This perhaps is going to sound corny, naïve, innocent or even foolish. I don’t know, but it’s what it’s. My partner and I met each other more than 15 years ago in a lost corner of the middle-south of Spain. For 10 years we maintain an on-distance relationship. It was a great relationship, with its good and bad things, but it was on distance. When I decided to move to Sweden, it was also because I wanted to start a new life with her, living under the same root. We got lucky and she got her dream position as a researcher in Finland and we decided to move here. I somehow wanted to enjoy and take back part of the time we were apart in Spain and try to share as much time as I could with her. We’ve been partners for life and I hope we will continue this way till the end of our lives. I’ve been really happy to be able to share all this time with her and travel together to the far side of the world. What an adventure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;traveling-and-discovering-the-world&quot;&gt;Traveling and discovering the World&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’ve been also doing a lot is, traveling. No, I haven’t been doing tourism. I don’t like that, I don’t want to collect places on an album. I really want to have experiences and try to know the places I go as much as I can. Explore the terrain. I’ve been really blessed that I’ve been able to do it during these years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-nordics&quot;&gt;The Nordics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve mentioned before, I’ve been living in Sweden and now I live in Finland, but I’ve in all the other Nordic Countries, but Iceland. When we moved to Finland and we knew that it was going to be permanent so we decided to move my old Volkswagen Golf from Spain to our place in Finland. We decided not to take any ferry and we crossed Denmark, Sweden from South to North and Finland from North to South till where we live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, we’ve been traveling all around the Nordics for business or leisure. We been in Lapland and in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Cape_(Norway)&quot;&gt;North Cape&lt;/a&gt; as well as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lofoten&quot;&gt;Lofototen&lt;/a&gt; islands and the North part of Norway, where we’ve been camping. We’ve camped also in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalparks.fi/urhokekkonennp&quot;&gt;Urho Kekonen&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalparks.fi/kolinp&quot;&gt;Koli&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nationalparks.fi/patvinsuonp&quot;&gt;Patvinsuo&lt;/a&gt; National Parks. And of course, we’ve hiked all around North Karelia and visited other parts of Finland. I even has witnessed a moose hunting on a weekend trip to the North of Finland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;europe&quot;&gt;Europe&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned previously, at some point we decided to move the my old Volkswagen Golf from Spain to Finland, so we drove all across Europe. It was a really wonderful —and tiring trip— in which we crossed, France, Belgium, Netherlands, Germany and part of the &lt;a href=&quot;#the-nordics&quot;&gt;Nordics&lt;/a&gt; and watched Europe pass by our windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been also Visiting Vienna and Zurich lately, two cities that I really love. I really love Center Europe, its architecture and of course its people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;usa&quot;&gt;USA&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017 we lived for five months in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Northwest&quot;&gt;Pacific Northwest of the USA&lt;/a&gt;. More specifically in the city of Corvallis.   For us was a wonderful experience that allowed us to discover the USA, specially the West part. For me it wasn’t the first time in the USA, since I was &lt;em&gt;living&lt;/em&gt; for a month in NYC in 2008 although you can argue that NYC isn’t exactly the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to Corvallis, we have the opportunity to discover America, or at least that part of America. We lived in a nice wooden old house close to the center of the city and had really interesting housemates, landlord and neighbors. Our neighborhood was like taken from one of those American movies of the 80s. Houses with lawns and streets full of trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also bought a car and cruise America a little bit in our spare time. We visited several National and State parks, where we enjoyed the American wilderness, and drove the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oregon_Coast&quot;&gt;Oregon Coast&lt;/a&gt; up and down several times.  Just to mention some of the places we were… &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oregon_Dunes_National_Recreation_Area&quot;&gt;Florence Dunes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Redwood_National_and_State_Parks&quot;&gt;Redwoods National Park&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crater_Lake&quot;&gt;Crater Lake National Park&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silver_Falls_State_Park&quot;&gt;Silver Falls State Park&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McKenzie_Pass&quot;&gt;McKenzie Pass&lt;/a&gt;… and of course we went East to visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arches_National_Park&quot;&gt;Archers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocky_Mountain_National_Park&quot;&gt;Rocky Mountain&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Teton_National_Park&quot;&gt;Grand Teton&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yellowstone_National_Park&quot;&gt;Yellowstone&lt;/a&gt; National Parks. We saw past by our window the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Oregon&quot;&gt;Eastern Oregon&lt;/a&gt; with its &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Desert_(Oregon)&quot;&gt;High Desert&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utah#Geography&quot;&gt;Utah desert&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyoming&quot;&gt;Wyoming&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyoming_Basin_shrub_steppe&quot;&gt;shrub steppe&lt;/a&gt; and we crossed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocky_Mountains&quot;&gt;Rocky Montains&lt;/a&gt;. Crossing the Rocky Mountains was specially adventurous since we did it partly at night&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I will never forget the shadow of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colorado_River&quot;&gt;Colorado river&lt;/a&gt; gorge agains the night ski while we rolled up the highway with the long semis overpassing us and the opposite lanes almost &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interstate_70_in_Colorado#Colorado_River&quot;&gt;overlay one over the other&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coming-across-of-interesting-people&quot;&gt;Coming across of interesting people&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everything while traveling has been just being mesmerized by wonderful landscapes, of course. I been doing something even more important, meeting people along the way. Some of them wonderful and some of them less wonderful. With some of them I had a long relation, and with others I just exchange few words. With some of them I still keep contact, and some of them are just memories. Some of them were natives, some of them were fellow travelers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting people is what makes traveling fun. Without people, places would be just empty and people is what make places wonderful or horrible. Talking with people is what make you see things differently and what really tell you the story of the place. From our trip to the USA we keep pretty fond memories of people, who usually were pretty social, and we are still in contact with most of the ones we interacted in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quantity-time&quot;&gt;Quantity time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-finnish&quot;&gt;Learning Finnish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first arrived to Finland I started to attend to the Finnish &lt;em&gt;Intensive&lt;/em&gt; courses the unemployment office provided as a way to learn the language and the culture. I was attending to those courses for a total of one year and a half during the first 3 years. Each course was around 500 hours during five or six months and they included &lt;em&gt;language internships&lt;/em&gt; in a Finnish company or organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say that I actually did learn Finnish —A 2.1 level— but not all the Finnish I wanted or I would like to have learned for the amount of time and effort in invested. However, there was a bright part on it, I meet people, I knew about their lives, the reasons why they ended up here, and and share quite interesting experiences with all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would I repeat those courses? no! but I have to say that the experience was worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;master&quot;&gt;Master&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Autumn 2013 I’ve been enrolled in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.igeon.eu&quot;&gt;iGEON&lt;/a&gt; online Master of Science and I was coursing it normally until I arrived to Finland. Then, I started with the Finnish courses that absorbed most of the time, my energy and my morale. Little by little I left it aside… because I wanted to do other things, like learning on my own, doing an internship to get some hands-on-knowledge, traveling or just enjoy some time with my loved ones and taking care of them. In other words, I got stuck for a while and my progress halted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’m resuming it right now again and I plan to &lt;strong&gt;finish it on 2020&lt;/strong&gt; or earlier if I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-on-my-own&quot;&gt;Learning on my own&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a really curious person and I like learning as a way to improve myself. During these years I’ve been learning and improving mostly about computers and programing, but also about other things. For example, how to bake &lt;a href=&quot;/archive/tags/bread&quot;&gt;bread&lt;/a&gt; and pizza as it should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the computer science department I’ve been mostly improving my skills scripting in environments like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_shell&quot;&gt;Unix shell&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cmd.exe&quot;&gt;Windows Batch&lt;/a&gt;. I also learned how to program in R and some statistics on my own, and I continue doing it and wanting to improve my coding. I’ve learned how to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-scm.com/&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; and I learned how to create static websites with &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cascading_Style_Sheets&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sass_(stylesheet_language)&quot;&gt;Sass&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://shopify.github.io/liquid/&quot;&gt;Liquid templating&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration&quot;&gt;Continuous Integration&lt;/a&gt; and some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruby_(programming_language)&quot;&gt;Ruby&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JavaScript&quot;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt;.. I’ve been also toying with Raspberries and using them as a home servers for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download-server/&quot;&gt;R Studio server&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openvpn.net&quot;&gt;VPN server&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samba_(software)&quot;&gt;NAS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nextcloud&quot;&gt;cloud storage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/01/18/convert-you-pi-in-an-airplay-receiver/&quot;&gt;wireless audio streaming&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pi-hole&quot;&gt;ad blocker&lt;/a&gt;, internet speed logger and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;internships&quot;&gt;Internships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve done a total of four internships, three of them related to my Finnish language courses and the last one was just a 6 month internship sponsored by the employment office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;metsäkeskus&quot;&gt;Metsäkeskus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the internship of my first Finnish language course I decided to go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metsakeskus.fi/&quot;&gt;Metsäkeskus&lt;/a&gt; so I could learn about Finnish forest and practice some Finnish at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience was really positive and I keep really fond memories of the people working there that I was able to interact with my little Finnish. I was lucky and my internship supervisor spoke English, as well as the director of the office, so we could workout something productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I visit the field a couple of times with my supervisor and other people from the office and I could witness on first hand how Finnish forest was managed. I also learned how the GIS of Metsäkeskus worked, how it was totally interrelated with the forest inventory in real time and how the customers could access to the data to take decisions about their own Forest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of my duties there were create a online map with the information from the Metsäkeskus’ forest inventory data, which was all in Finnish and I have to translate and understand on my own. I processed and analyzed all the data and lately we published it on the Metsäkeskus site, where it was for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;uef&quot;&gt;UEF&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my second language course onwards, I decided carry on my internships at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uef.fi/&quot;&gt;University of Eastern of Finland&lt;/a&gt;, where I could learn about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lidar&quot;&gt;LiDAR&lt;/a&gt; and how to process it. I had some contact with LiDAR before but I never ever processed it that intensively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I download and analyzed the LiDAR data of the whole Finland using Windows Batch Scripts and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fs.fed.us/eng/rsac/fusion/launch/fusionbkg.htm&quot;&gt;Fusion&lt;/a&gt; software from the US Forest Service. Then, I storage and manage the outcome in a geodatabases and it could be accessed much faster than in its raw format. I also analyze LiDAR data using R and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Jean-Romain/lidR&quot;&gt;LidR&lt;/a&gt; package, using parallelization processing, to yield biomass estimation form the LiDAR data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;researching&quot;&gt;Researching&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the outcomes of the internships at the UEF was a scientific publication in the iForest journal that I actively helped to write and soon will be published since it’s been already accepted. During the writing process I learned how to read and write science and how hard is researching and learn to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researching is a career that I’ve been toying with a little bit. I am very excited about the possibility of continue doing research and to further developed research related activities. I’ve been always curious about science and technology and I think I have a rational and analytical mind that could server me well in in scientific activities. However, I have a too much respect for science and I don’t like the stiffness of academia, but I don’t think both things could be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coaching&quot;&gt;Coaching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During these last years I’ve been also “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coaching&quot;&gt;coaching&lt;/a&gt;” other people. When I say coaching I mean mainly giving advice —when I’ve been asked for it— professional or personal one. Please, don’t think that I’m that arrogant and condescending to think my advice is better than anyone else’s that I’ve been giving it “freely” all around to everyone. I usually don’t mind anyone business, but mine. Howeer, when I see my close ones troubled I usually ask what is going on and if I think can share some kind of wisdom or experience I have that can help, there I go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My working experience has served me well in this field since I worked in high stressful environments that allowed me realize of the importance of the team and that learn how to manage people in your team it will really make the difference. This made me really interested in the &lt;a href=&quot;#the-fifth-discipline&quot;&gt;topic&lt;/a&gt; and I’ve tried to learn as much as I could. I’m proud to say that I still keep a really good relation with all my previous team-mates, that were over, under or lateral to me, and that some of them became friends later on. Some of them told me they felt that I wasn’t there to command but to help them to fulfill their job, which I tried to do as much I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this matter, I tried to support my wife as much as I possible in her endeavor of get a PhD and more than once, specially towards the end, I gave her a &lt;em&gt;pep talk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to &lt;em&gt;boost&lt;/em&gt; her up as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;volunteering&quot;&gt;Volunteering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that the idea and purpose of volunteering is quite different between Europe and America, mainly North America, or at less that is my perspective being Spanish and living in Finland. I feel that almost every North American has volunteering in something at some point of their live, while in Europe is something more rare, or that at least is more related to political activism —like conservationism, ecology, or something similar— than to general volunteering. Almost none of the people is close to me and live in Spain has volunteering to anything at any given point of their lives. I guess that it’s related to what is socially expected and to the different perspective about the State and what is its role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, I’ve been doing some volunteering during these last years, but probably not as much for the North American standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cultural-integration-volunteering&quot;&gt;Cultural integration volunteering&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the first years we lived in Joensuu a friend of us created a small group of people —sort of a club or association— to help to develop a little bit the cultural life of Joensuu. We meet regularly in one of the rooms of the regional museum and developed some activities together like art expositions, international food activities or photo sessions with locals and internationals to try to tell a little bit their stories. We also developed some cultural activities for refugees and their children, like an exposition of the children’s drawings about war, so we could create some awareness about what was going on in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;teaching-to-code&quot;&gt;Teaching to code&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife and I organized an activity to teach code to kids on fifth grade on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/WGSAoPUJJty&quot;&gt;CEIP José Calvo Sotelo&lt;/a&gt; in Madrid inside of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hourofcode.com/us/learn&quot;&gt;Hour of Code&lt;/a&gt; initiative. It was really interesting to see how kids were really interesting in computers, beyond playing computer games, and how they can think out of the box to solve problems in different ways. It was a really boost in creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;carousel&quot;&gt;Carousel&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s funny how to you can end up in the most interesting places sometimes just by pure chance. While we were living in the US I ended up helping to restore an old &lt;a href=&quot;http://albanycarousel.com&quot;&gt;carousel&lt;/a&gt; in a town close to the one we were living and it was one of the most positive experiences in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we traveled to the US West Coast, we were looking for a place to live and we ended up contacted by a nice couple because they perhaps had some place for us to stay. It didn’t workout —because their place was too far away of the center of our activities and we didn’t planned to have a car— but we ended up befriending.  They offered us a lot of support and help during all our stay there and they are one of the best people we came across in our lives. It’s funny because the main reason they contacted us is because we were living in Finland. She has a Finnish ancestry and they were curios about Finland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, he was volunteering restoring this old &lt;a href=&quot;http://albanycarousel.com&quot;&gt;carousel&lt;/a&gt; and they asked me if I wanted to go with him. Right away. I came across a really nice bunch of old school people that were carrying out a really complex engineering project, just for fun! I couldn’t ask for more. It was great to help them to install the floor, review the mechanics, install the animals, or just to put some bulbs in the carrousel. However, the best was to be in contact with them and know a little bit of their stories. They were living in the surroundings all their lives and they were part of the 50s and 60s generation that witnessed America’s splendor. They were really kind to me and, even when I arrived in the last stages of the project, they didn’t hesitate to put my name with theirs hidden in one the beans of the carrousel, like any other member of the team. I even appear in a PBS documentary about the restoration and in some photos in the local newspaper about the topic. I think I was exotic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;entanglement&quot;&gt;Entanglement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I don’t have my life that extremely compartmentalized. All of these things and much more have been and are entangle… mixed together as in any other life. Lives are organic and usually their parts can’t be put in different boxes because they end up dying. Of course you can dissect lives, like any other system, to understand them better, but they are a whole and they need to be understood that way. Looking at just parts doesn’t make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;x-large&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fifth_Discipline&quot;&gt;When you split an elephant in two, you do not have two small elephants which you can take care of…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-all-of-these-just-bullit&quot;&gt;Is all of these just bull**it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps… or perhaps not. What it’s true is we are usually much more of that we manage to show to the rest of the people, for good or bad. I wanted to be a little bit more transparent and show that although curriculums could be good tools, but most times they left out of the picture a lot of what a person is. That is problematic. Anyway, no tool is perfect and even this post is just &lt;em&gt;part of the story&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:0&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Both of us know that this post isn’t going to be small. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:0&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I don’t think that getting a diploma —going to the university to get some degree of formal education— fully equated to &lt;strong&gt;learning&lt;/strong&gt; and gather knowledge. I know a lot of people that has several diplomas, even PhDs but they barely know anything. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s pretty clear Optimistic Nihilism isn’t a real philosophical term but a casual lingo. But perhaps you can learn a little bit more about the term in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/TUtwbA&quot;&gt;answer in Quora&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The original idea was to camp by the Colorado close to to Arches National Park, but it was too hot. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A pep talk is: &lt;em&gt;Informal&lt;/em&gt; A speech of exhortation, as to a team or staff, meant to instill enthusiasm or bolster morale. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wordnik.com/words/pep%20talk&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;. But could be also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Pep%20Talk&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/02/03/what-Ive-been-doing-these-last-years/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;What have I been doing these last years?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="life" />
      
        <category term="developing" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since some people has asked me this once in a while, I think it's going to be a good idea to write a small0 post about what I've been doing these last years since I left Spain. I think I'm going to give it the shape of an informal resume / curriculum where I'm going to talk, superficially, about each of the things I've been doing.</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/existential-nihilism-header.jpeg" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Analyzing my personality. Bottom line</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/01/20/analyzing-my-personality-bottom-line/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing my personality. Bottom line" />
      <published>2019-01-20T16:50:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-20T16:50:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/01/20/analyzing-my-personality-bottom-line</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/01/20/analyzing-my-personality-bottom-line/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/16personalities.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        

        &lt;p&gt;This is just the final post of the series of post about &lt;a href=&quot;/archive/tags/my-personality&quot;&gt;my personality&lt;/a&gt;. It’s been quite fun, but really hard, analyzing myself —or try to— from the starting point of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/&quot;&gt;16pernalities&lt;/a&gt; test. I wanted to write the &lt;em&gt;final conclusion&lt;/em&gt; as a separate post mainly because I want it to encroach all the other three post and I don’t think this bit really fit at the bottom of any of the others, even when It’s going to be small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason I’ve done this exercise —analyze myself— is &lt;strong&gt;improvement&lt;/strong&gt;. If one doesn’t know well oneself, how one can really improve and try to be a better version of oneself? First time I read the test I really thought that it was more or less shenanigans and I still hold that opinion, since no test is going to give you, &lt;strong&gt;ever&lt;/strong&gt;, a real picture of yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I think it’s probably a great tool to know myself better and to walk me through the strong and weak point of my personality. Whether the test is really accurate in framing your personality, it create a interesting template or structure to dip you deeper into yourself. I never thought before in some of the points that the description of my personality raised and, of course, I never thought in evaluating them. So I really think it’s worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second great reason is &lt;strong&gt;sharing&lt;/strong&gt;. I really wanted to share my personality with the rest of the world. Not because I really think I’m that important to anyone to give a damn about how my personality is, but as an exercise of openness. Usually, when someone talks about you, and they are more or less accurate, we get concerned, angry, even mad at them and try to hide as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a perfectly natural behavior, since we are afraid to get hurt by others if we’re too exposed, but it’s something that has to change, even more if the description isn’t done with malice. When we share with others how we are and why, we are making it easy for them to &lt;a href=&quot;http://radicalteacher.com/uploads/SengeISeeYou.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;see us&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, understand us and in the end communicate. Trying to understand others and make it easy to understand us make us a better humans. Trying to find out what are the views of others and why and how they reached them it’s a much better start for a dialogue, instead of just fighting those views when they aren’t close to ours. Sharing what you are and how you see the world, it’s a great place to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing your flaws doesn’t expose you to others, just make you human and a better and more hones person. No one is perfect&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;… Let’s try to find out about each other more often, so we can understand each other better, work better and live better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;What is more… what is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perfection&quot;&gt;perfection&lt;/a&gt;? Perfection is a human concept that at the end of the day has nothing to do with reality. Some that for someone could be perfect, to others can be totally imperfect. The same for different situations. Someone can be just &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; for someone, but totally &lt;em&gt;imperfect&lt;/em&gt; for other one. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/01/20/analyzing-my-personality-bottom-line/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Analyzing my personality. Bottom line&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="my personality" />
      
        <category term="science" />
      
        <category term="work" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is just the final post of the series of post about my personality. It’s been quite fun, but really hard, analyzing myself —or try to— from the starting point of the 16pernalities test. I wanted to write the final conclusion as a separate post mainly because I want it to encroach all the other three post and I don’t think this bit really fit at the bottom of any of the others, even when It’s going to be small.</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/16personalities.png" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">My other personality trails</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/01/08/my-other-personality-trails/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My other personality trails" />
      <published>2019-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/01/08/my-other-personality-trails</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/01/08/my-other-personality-trails/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/personality.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        

        &lt;figure class=&quot;align-left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/Screen-Shot-2018-05-02-at-20.26.39-1.png&quot; title=&quot;General idea of what it seems I’m
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/Screen-Shot-2018-05-02-at-20.26.39-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;General idea of what is seems I'm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      General idea of what it seems I’m

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been trying to &lt;em&gt;dissect&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/archive/tags/my-personality/&quot;&gt;my personality&lt;/a&gt; using the results on the 16personalities test in previous posts and I would like to finish talking about how they think my &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Five_personality_traits&quot;&gt;big 5 trails are&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the picture in the left. They think I have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mind:&lt;/strong&gt; Extraverted (78%) vs. introverted (22%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Energy:&lt;/strong&gt; Observant (58%) vs. intuitive (42%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nature:&lt;/strong&gt; Thinking (53%) vs. feeling (47%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tactics:&lt;/strong&gt; Prospecting (51%) vs. judging (49%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity:&lt;/strong&gt; Assertive (76%) vs. turbulent (24%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to talk a little bit about each of the trails and see how I really fit —or I think I fit— on those results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mind-extraverted-vs-introverted&quot;&gt;Mind: Extraverted vs. Introverted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-right&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 300px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/images/theory/traits/16personalities_extraverted.png&quot; title=&quot;Extraverted person. Source: 16personalities
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/images/theory/traits/16personalities_extraverted.png&quot; alt=&quot;Extraverted person&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Extraverted person. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/mind-introverted-vs-extraverted&quot;&gt;16personalities&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In their opinion&lt;/strong&gt;, I’m extraverted (78%) vs. introverted (22%), which means I’m a highly extraverted person. However, and as they point out at the end of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/mind-introverted-vs-extraverted&quot;&gt;description about this trail&lt;/a&gt;, one shouldn’t confuse introversion / extraversion with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Introspection&quot;&gt;introspection&lt;/a&gt;. One person can be quite introverted and at the same time be reflective. On the other hand one can be extraverted and introspect, which actually I think &lt;a href=&quot;http://tcat.tc/1PJ4yUZ&quot;&gt;I’m&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really never have considered myself an extraverted person, at least for the standard we have in Spain as an extraverted individual. I see myself more introverted than extroverted, but since I live in Finland, and I have had some experience living in other places, I need to make the following question: compare with whom am I extraverted or introverted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experience has make me more extroverted. When I was a kid, I was much more introverted than I’m right now, but with the past of time and the experiences I have had in my life, I’ve, little by little, learned to be less &lt;em&gt;fearful&lt;/em&gt; of the outside world. In other words, you lose the fear to fail when you finally understand that usually it isn’t such a big deal and it’s part of the process of learning and living. In the end, it gives you confidence in yourself and you become more extraverted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, and reading directly from their description of the trail, they mention that extroverts &lt;em&gt;are not as sensitive to outer stimuli and need to seek them out in order to gain a kind of functional equilibrium and to perform well&lt;/em&gt;, which is somehow true in my case. I really need to have social interaction to survive —who doesn’t?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:0&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;— and I miss the social life I get when I’m in the South of Europe or in the on the &lt;em&gt;other side of the pond&lt;/em&gt;, where social life is different —more dynamic— than in the North of Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also mention that extroverts are &lt;em&gt;willing to take the lead&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;push the limits for them and for others&lt;/em&gt; and that they &lt;em&gt;feel they can handle any chalenge&lt;/em&gt;, which I would say that it’s more or less true in my case. Yet, I really don’t know if I can attribute that to my nature, personality or, again, to experience. Regarding to taking the lead, I prefer rather not, even more if I feel there are someone more willing, and qualified&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, than me. In relation of taking &lt;em&gt;any challenge&lt;/em&gt;, it’s also true that I’m usually quite eager, but it isn’t the first time that I go with overconfidence. &lt;em&gt;Live an learn&lt;/em&gt; they say. Seems that &lt;em&gt;extraverts are much more proactive in experiencing (and relying on) the world around them&lt;/em&gt;, which somehow I can also relate to me, since I like places full or energy and activities and social life, in other words, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fp_b3PnsPPs&quot;&gt;I like cities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we have to take into account that this seems to be just a measure of how much a external stimuli a person can handle. So, it isn’t probably the same concept that people have of extroverts —someone shouting around— or introverts —someone that it’s only able to look to their shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, something called my attention in the description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;x-large&quot;&gt;Introverts are more likely to dislike coffee and energy drinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are most of the Finnish people extraverted because they love caffeine? I doubt it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;energy-observant-vs-intuitive&quot;&gt;Energy: Observant vs. Intuitive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-left&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 300px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/images/theory/traits/16personalities_observant.png&quot; title=&quot;Observant person. Source: 16personalities
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/images/theory/traits/16personalities_observant.png&quot; alt=&quot;Observant person&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Observant person. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/energy-intuitive-vs-observant&quot;&gt;16personalities&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…how you see the world and what kind of information you focus on. It may seem like your decisions are the most important, but a decision is only as good as the understanding that backs it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that I’m in between two worlds here… they consider me &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/energy-intuitive-vs-observant&quot;&gt;observant (58%) vs. intuitive (42%)&lt;/a&gt;, and more or less it’s true in my opinion. I think this has a really positive side, because you can end with the best of two worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m able to dream, to wonder, to make questions and to think how to improve the world around me. And even sometimes, I do it too much. However, and at the same time, want to take into account reality, the current state of matters, data and facts and being concrete on those thoughts. In other words, I’m a &lt;strong&gt;realistic dreamer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nature-thinking-vs-feeling&quot;&gt;Nature: Thinking vs. Feeling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this camp, it seems that I’m also between two worlds, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/nature-thinking-vs-feeling&quot;&gt;thinking (53%) vs. feeling (47%&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking people are usually rational and follow logic; they tend to use their brains more than their hearts. On the other hand, feeling people, are more compassionate towards other and passionate defending their believes. It seems that I’m more or less in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a quite logical person, and try to be also analytical. I think that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Systems_theory&quot;&gt;System Thinking&lt;/a&gt; is a great tool to understand the world and that more or less everything has a systemic answer and solution. I usually, don’t like to draw conclusions soon and I like to check all the sides of a problems, looking for the root cause. This perhaps has to do with me being an engineer, since I really think this is the most efficient way to operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, and as a good Spaniard, I quite passionate, and when I feel —and I usually know with data and facts— that something is someway different as usually people think it’s or it can be solved in some other better way as usually is, I will vehemently defend those truths until their last consequences. You’ve probably guested it… my favorite color is &lt;strong class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;red&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tactics-judging-vs-prospecting&quot;&gt;Tactics: Judging vs. Prospecting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-right&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 300px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/images/theory/traits/16personalities_prospecting.png&quot; title=&quot;Prospecting person. Source: 16personalities
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/images/theory/traits/16personalities_prospecting.png&quot; alt=&quot;Prospecting person&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Prospecting person. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/tactics-judging-vs-prospecting&quot;&gt;16personalities&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the last trail where I’m &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2oyhlad64-s&quot;&gt;between two waters&lt;/a&gt; since I’m &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/tactics-judging-vs-prospecting&quot;&gt;prospecting (51%) vs. judging (49%)&lt;/a&gt;. And provably the one I disagree more with the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say that judging people like to have everything planned and always have a plan B, C, D —and so on and so forth— that they prefer clarity, they like checklists and that they really follow an order —and law— which usually translates into that they have a strong work ethic too. In other words, they aren’t flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…if you see someone walk for five minutes so that they could get to the other side of the street using a crosswalk, they are much more likely to be a Judging type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, prospectors are much more flexible and relaxed when dealing with expected and unexpected challenges, they like to have their options open and it’s difficult to commit to something forever for them, since in the future it could turn out to be an inferior option. They usually focus in their happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;they always be able to come up with something better to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This really make me to have mixed feeling, because in on one side I’m not really that stiff person as a judging people seem to be. I definitely like to have my options open although I usually have a contingency plan at hand in case something happens. In other words I like to have something prepare to deal with the unexpected even though I’m not afraid of dealing with it and improvise if it’s necessary. And of course, I have a strong work ethic and I’m perfectly able to commit. What is more, I usually think I commit to much to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identity-assertive-vs-turbulent&quot;&gt;Identity: Assertive vs. Turbulent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish, it seems that I’m &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/identity-assertive-vs-turbulent&quot;&gt;assertive (76%) vs. turbulent (24%)&lt;/a&gt; in the camp of identity. Yet, I don’t fully agree with that percentages, I think they reflect some of my personality and even in some cases, on things I really want to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that I’m quite stress resistant, as I’ve mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/11/13/the-explorer-with-the-people-mastery/#stress-resistant&quot;&gt;earlier&lt;/a&gt;, and also consider myself fairly self-assured and even-tempered. I’m reasonably satisfied with my life and I’m not afraid of taking challenges or afraid of the ones that, for sure, I’m going to come across in my life —sooner or later. I also think that it’s usually no point into analyze what you have done in the past and even more regret your decisions. Sure, you need to learn from your past, from what you have done and figure out why things turned out the way they turned. But you shouldn’t attach your past to your ankle like a &lt;em&gt;ball and chain&lt;/em&gt; in a way that it cripple your future. The important is the present and future and what you are going to do on and with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, I’m someone that is always eager to improve and I always want to learn new things. I’m quite perfectionist and I’ve needed to learn that sometimes you don’t need to be that perfectionist to get things done. Sometimes that perfectionism has made perhaps not to push harder to reach my goals in life —if you aren’t going to be able to reach perfection, what is the point on trying?. Lucky, it’s something I’ve learned to deal with, using productivity techniques such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;pomodoro&lt;/a&gt; technique, agile, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Getting_Things_Done&quot;&gt;getting things done&lt;/a&gt; and similar. Productivity is something I’m been always interested on. At the end of the day, I’m an engineer, I really like to optimice and improve things around me, including myself, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:0&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Finns :finland:. Or they say so. But I don’t believe it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:0&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I don’t consider myself specially qualified to lead. I like to learn about it and I think that most people have the wrong concept of leadership —the commanding one— while leading is a really complex position  that has to do more with helping others to find their own way and perhaps pointing the direction —but this can easily be confuse with forcing to go in that direction— than with command. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yeah, I love cities, specially big cities, where people is really social and I always get mesmerized by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_Lights&quot;&gt;city lights&lt;/a&gt;. However, please don’t get me wrong, I love to explore, to camp away in the wild —not in a camping if possible— and enjoy the outdoors. If I didn’t, I couldn’t be Forest Engineer, but as Madona said: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fp_b3PnsPPs&quot;&gt;I don’t like cities but I love New York&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve been reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40876575-utopia-for-realists&quot;&gt;Utopia for Realist&lt;/a&gt;, and the book open with a quote from Oscar Wilde: &lt;em&gt;“A map of the world that does not include Utopia is not worth even glancing at, for it leaves out the one country at which Humanity is always landing. And when Humanity lands there, it looks out, and, seeing a better country, sets sail. Progress is the realization of Utopias.”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2019/01/08/my-other-personality-trails/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;My other personality trails&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="my personality" />
      
        <category term="science" />
      
        <category term="work" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I've been trying to dissect my results in the 16personalities test about [my personality](/archive/tags/my-personality/) in previous posts and I would like to continue, and finish talking about how they think my [big 5 trails are](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Five_personality_traits).</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/personality.jpg" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Happy New Year 12019 🎊</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/12/31/happy-new-year-12019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy New Year 12019 🎊" />
      <published>2018-12-31T06:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2018-12-31T06:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/12/31/happy-new-year-12019</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/12/31/happy-new-year-12019/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/The-Year-12019-header.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        

        &lt;p class=&quot;xx-large&quot;&gt;I want to wish you all a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center gigantic&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Happy New Year &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=czgOWmtGVGs&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/The-Year-12019-calendar.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The 12019 Human Era Calendar from Kurzgesagt. Source: Standard.tv
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/The-Year-12019-calendar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The 12019 Human Era Calendar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      The 12019 Human Era Calendar from &lt;a href=&quot;https://kurzgesagt.org/&quot;&gt;Kurzgesagt&lt;/a&gt;. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://standard.tv/collections/in-a-nutshell/products/in-a-nutshell-12-019-human-era-calendar?variant=12538876854327&quot;&gt;Standard.tv&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;xx-large&quot;&gt;And make you remember that…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center x-large&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’ve Made An Enormous Progress In The Last 13000 Years&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://j.gifs.com/zK2yyr.gif&quot; title=&quot;From hunters and gatherers to programmers. Source
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://j.gifs.com/zK2yyr.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      From hunters and gatherers to programmers. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=czgOWmtGVGs&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center x-large&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From Hunters And Gatherers To Programmers And Space Explorers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://j.gifs.com/rRQnlw.gif&quot; title=&quot;Voyager leaving the Solar System. Source
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://j.gifs.com/rRQnlw.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Voyager leaving the Solar System. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NN3ppVemVhQ&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center x-large&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And Although The Way Till Here Haven’t Been Easy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://j.gifs.com/G5PokQ.gif&quot; title=&quot;Is war over? Source
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://j.gifs.com/G5PokQ.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Is war over? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NbuUW9i-mHs&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center gigantic&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There Are Always Reasons&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;To Be Optimistic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Courtesy of embedresponsively.com //--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;responsive-video-container&quot;&gt;

  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/MBRqu0YOH14&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center xx-large&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And To See The Beautiful Side Of Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Courtesy of embedresponsively.com //--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;responsive-video-container&quot;&gt;

  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/-O5kNPlUV7w&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-center xx-large&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And Remember That You Get&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“More Bonus Points If You Help To Build A Galactic Human Empire”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//gifs.com/embed/bonus-points-W7gXZQ?muted=false&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450em&quot; style=&quot;-webkit-backface-visibility: hidden;-webkit-transform: scale(1);&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;xx-large&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:1em&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS/ This is our &lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;2018 in review:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/O+L-2018-in-review-EN.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;12018 in review
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/O+L-2018-in-review-EN.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;span style=&quot;color: #ff0000;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;2018 in review

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/12/31/happy-new-year-12019/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Happy New Year 12019 🎊&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="New Year" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I want to wish you all a</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/The-Year-12019-header.jpg" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How I schedule post in Jekyll</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/12/03/how-i-schedule-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I schedule post in Jekyll" />
      <published>2018-12-03T09:14:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2018-12-03T09:14:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/12/03/how-i-schedule-post</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/12/03/how-i-schedule-post/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/jekyll+travis.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        

        &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/11/26/how-i-publish-my-blog-ci/&quot;&gt;other day&lt;/a&gt; I was explaining how I publish my blog using CI. Today I want to explain how I schedule post in my blog while still involving CI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know that &lt;a href=&quot;/archive/tags/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is great, but sometimes it’s lacking some features, like be able to schedule post. I don’t think it’s a dealbreaker, but it’s definitely helpful. Sometimes I write a couple of post at once, just because they are part of a series, or a single post that is split because it’s really big, or just because I like to… However, I don’t want to publish those post right away so I would like to schedule them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Jekyll you can’t schedule post because when you build your site, it’s static —isn’t this the whole point of having a static site?— so unless you build your site again it isn’t going to change. So, even if you set a date in the future in the yaml front-matter nothing is going to happen unless you rebuild the site on that date or after that date. Other option is to build with with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--future&lt;/code&gt; tag, but then those post will show when you build which it’s going to be probably too early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several solutions out there to schedule, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://serverless.com/blog/static-site-post-scheduler/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, this &lt;a href=&quot;https://forestry.io/blog/automatically-publish-scheduled-posts-for-static-site/#option-2-using-a-lambda-task-to-trigger-your-build&quot;&gt;other&lt;/a&gt; or that &lt;a href=&quot;http://brettterpstra.com/2013/01/17/scheduling-posts-with-jekyll/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;. However, most of those are too complicate for my taste, or you need to have &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; on AWS, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I have a &lt;a href=&quot;/archive/tags/raspberry-pi&quot;&gt;Raspberry pi&lt;/a&gt; at home, it’s connected to internet all the time and all the time it’s on, I can schedule &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron&quot;&gt;cron jobs&lt;/a&gt; on it to run scripts. On the other side, you can trigger your site rebuild on Travis using &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/triggering-builds/&quot;&gt;their API&lt;/a&gt;. I’m already doing that with a cron job to rebuild my site everyday at 8 in the morning. Cron it’s really handy and allow you a lot of different &lt;a href=&quot;https://crontab.guru&quot;&gt;setups&lt;/a&gt;. For instance, you can run a script every minute, every six hours, once a week, once a month, a year… etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-cron&quot;&gt;What is cron?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just in case you don’t know or you are so lazy that you can’t check the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, I’m going to sum up for you what is cron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cron is just a scheduler for jobs that most of UNIX machines —linux and mac for example— have. It’s really basic, but really handy if you know more or less how to program it. I recommend you to learn how to use it because can make your life quite easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-you-access-to-travis-api&quot;&gt;How do you access to Travis API&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/triggering-builds/&quot;&gt;travis documentation&lt;/a&gt; you can find more options, but this is the basic script you need to run on cron —or on your terminal— if you want to access Travis API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-sh highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env bash&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'{
&quot;request&quot;: {
&quot;branch&quot;:&quot;master&quot;
}}'&lt;/span&gt;

curl &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-X&lt;/span&gt; POST &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-H&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Content-Type: application/json&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-H&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Accept: application/json&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-H&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Travis-API-Version: 3&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-H&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Authorization: token YOUR-TOKEN&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
   https://api.travis-ci.com/repo/your-github-username%2Fyour-repo-name/requests
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get your Travis token on your &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.com/account/preferences&quot;&gt;preferences page&lt;/a&gt; on Travis page. You also need to set &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;your-github-username&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;your-repo-name&lt;/code&gt; in the url. Remember you also need to make your script executable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;chmod&lt;/span&gt; +x path/to/your/script.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;running-jobs-in-cron&quot;&gt;Running jobs in cron&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to add jobs to cron you just need run in the terminal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;crontab &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-e&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you default text editor will open. There you can add jobs taking into account the following &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron#Overview&quot;&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;┌───────────── minute (0 - 59)
│ ┌───────────── hour (0 - 23)
│ │ ┌───────────── day of the month (1 - 31)
│ │ │ ┌───────────── month (1 - 12)
│ │ │ │ ┌───────────── day of the week (0 - 6) (Sunday to Saturday;
│ │ │ │ │                                   7 is also Sunday on some systems)
│ │ │ │ │
│ │ │ │ │
* * * * * command to execute # You can put a comment here too. 
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;command to execute&lt;/code&gt; is where you put the route to your script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if I wanted to run my building script on Nov 26th at 6.07 am I have to set up the following line in cron:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;7 6 26 11 * /root/scripts/cron-builds-jekyll/luispuerto-net.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can set up as much lines you want in cron, so you can set up multiple post at once for different dates and so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--warning&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Please mind in what time zone is your blog and in what time zone is your Pi —or whatever you are using to schedule post— because if they aren’t in the same time zone you need to take into account when you schedule your cron job. For example, I have my blog in UTC but my Pi is with me in Finland —EET— so I need to subtract two hours in winter and three in summer —mind the DST too if &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeanddate.com/news/time/europe-dst-end-2018.html&quot;&gt;it’s still happening&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-im-out-home&quot;&gt;When I’m out home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I’m out of home and I still want to program my post I still use my raspberry at home, since I can connect to it using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pivpn.io&quot;&gt;VPN connection&lt;/a&gt; I have set it up on the Raspberry. I recommend you to set it up a VPN if you haven’t done it yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-options&quot;&gt;Other options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a Raspberry, there are other options so you can run cron jobs &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=cron+jobs+online&amp;amp;t=osx&amp;amp;ia=web&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;. However, I haven’t tried any of those solutions and I don’t know how well suited are for running scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/12/03/how-i-schedule-post/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;How I schedule post in Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="jekyll" />
      
        <category term="blogging" />
      
        <category term="CI" />
      
        <category term="travis" />
      
        <category term="raspberry pi" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The other day I was explaining how I publish my blog using CI. Today I want to explain how I schedule post in my blog while still involving CI.</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/jekyll+travis.png" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How I publish my blog: Using Continuous Integration with Jekyll</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/26/how-i-publish-my-blog-ci/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I publish my blog: Using Continuous Integration with Jekyll" />
      <published>2018-11-26T08:07:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2018-11-26T08:07:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/26/how-i-publish-my-blog-ci</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/26/how-i-publish-my-blog-ci/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/jekyll+travis.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        

        &lt;p&gt;As I’ve mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/07/23/new-web-in-jekyll/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, this blog is build as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Static_web_page&quot;&gt;static website&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, which allow me not to worry about data bases, logins or anything of the sorts when I’m publishing and managing the web. I use the free tier of &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; as hosting, which has its downsides and upsides. The main upside is, it’s really convenient and free. On the other hand, I’m limited to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/versions/&quot;&gt;certain Jekyll plugins&lt;/a&gt; if I want to use GitHub Pages building capabilities. This can be circumnavigate if you use CI (Continuous Integration) to build your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-continuous-integration&quot;&gt;What is Continuous Integration?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more about this in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; —and in &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/for-beginners/#what-is-continuous-integration-ci&quot;&gt;Travis documentation&lt;/a&gt;— but CI is basically —and I’m summarizing a lot here— just testing your code before you &lt;em&gt;integrate&lt;/em&gt; —merge— it with the master branch, so you know that you aren’t breaking anything —serious. Usually what you do is &lt;em&gt;building&lt;/em&gt; your copy and then you merge it with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch. However, building is a pain, and even more if you have to do it all the time —continuously. For this reason, the CI services were born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually a CI works as it follows —again simplified:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s usually related / connected to your online repo and when you push commits to the repo the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Webhook&quot;&gt;webhooks&lt;/a&gt; are triggered and CI comes into action.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CI download the last commits of your repo to a machine —usually virtual— with an OS you can specify and begin tu run a series of scripts&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to test and to build your software from the last commit you’ve pushed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If those scripts give an error, so your code can’t be &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt;, report to you as failing and —bad luck— you have to review what you have done because it’s not working.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the scripts exit without an error —you’re lucky— and now a couple of things can happen.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Just nothing else. You are notify there is not errors in your code —so you are free to merge.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The code is automatically deployed.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;It’s merged into another branch —usually &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;It’s deploy to a server or something else.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these steps have a lot of sense in GitHub, GitLab and other repo online services where webhooks can be triggered even with a pull request, so you can know beforehand if someone else code is worth to review in an even of a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s more of less the official function of the CI. However, it can do much more than that. For example, in the Homebrew repos/taps it builds the bottles and deploys them to a hosting so you can latter download them. It can build software and apps and deploy it to your website. Or like in our case can build your Jekyll site and deploy to GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how&quot;&gt;How?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several options out there as CI services, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.com&quot;&gt;Travis&lt;/a&gt; —with is one of the most common one— to &lt;a href=&quot;https://jenkins.io&quot;&gt;Jenkins&lt;/a&gt; or, if you use &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/product/continuous-integration/&quot;&gt;GitLab, their own CI&lt;/a&gt;. I’m going to talk about Travis, because it’s the one I’m using myself and usually is the easier option. You can use Travis for free on the condition &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.com/plans&quot;&gt;your project is open source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;give-access-to-travis&quot;&gt;Give access to Travis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, you should go to the Travis website and authorize them to have access to your repos in GitHub. Usually, you just need to login with your GitHub account; they will ask for permission and if you just want to use Travis in all your repos or in just some of the repos. I have it set for only the repos I’m interested on because otherwise Travis can be trigged just pushing a commit to GitHub&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;configure-your-build&quot;&gt;Configure your build&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have given access to Travis to the repo where you have your Jekyll page, you need to configure your build. You configure your build with the file &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; in the root of your repo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is mine right now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-ruby highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30
31
32
33
34
35
36
37
38
39
40
41
42
43
44
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# .travis.yml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# This file should be at the root of your project&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;language: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ruby&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;rvm:
 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;2.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;cache:
  bundler: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# directories:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#   - $TRAVIS_BUILD_DIR/tmp/.htmlproofer&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;before_install:
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gem&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;install&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bundler&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;gemfile: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Gemfile&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;script:
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;$TRAVIS_BRANCH&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;master&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bundle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;jekyll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;algolia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
      &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;JEKYLL_ENV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;production&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bundle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;jekyll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;build&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bundle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;htmlproofer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;alt_ignore&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;/.*/&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;allow_hash_href&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;http&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ignore&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;999&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;disable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;external&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt; 
  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;$TRAVIS_BRANCH&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;develop&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;JEKYLL_ENV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;production&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bundle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;jekyll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;build&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bundle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;htmlproofer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;alt_ignore&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;/.*/&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;allow_hash_href&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;http&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ignore&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;999&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;disable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;external&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;branches:
  only:
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Change this to gh-pages if you're deploying using the gh-pages branch&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;master&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;develop&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;env:
  global:
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;NOKOGIRI_USE_SYSTEM_LIBRARIES&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# speeds up installation of html-proofer&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;sudo: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# route your build to the container-based infrastructure for a faster build&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;deploy:
  provider: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pages&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;skip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;cleanup: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;github&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;token: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;vg&quot;&gt;$GITHUB_TOKEN&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Set in the settings page of your repository, as a secure variable&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;keep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;history: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;local_dir: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# repo: luispuerto/luispuerto.net # in case I wanted to build my page in other repo&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;branch: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pages&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;on:
    branch: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;master&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can learn more about how to create your own configuration file on &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com&quot;&gt;Travis Documentation&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ll walk you through my config:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/tutorial/#selecting-a-different-programming-language&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;language&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: The language we are going to use in the build. In our case is Ruby, because Jekyll is build in Ruby.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/languages/ruby/#Supported-Ruby-Versions&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rvm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: is the version of ruby we want to use. I’m using the last one —at this moment— 2.5.3. I don’t know if you can set it up to use the last stable one, but some people argue that it isn’t a good idea and you should set the version so it match the one in your machine —which has sense&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/caching/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cache&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: You can cache content that usually don’t change. In our case we are caching the bundle install because usually the gems we need don’t change that often.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/installing-dependencies/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;before_install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Before we install the gems we are going to need to build our page we need to install the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/tutorials/using-jekyll-with-bundler/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/languages/ruby/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gemfile&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Location of the gemfile, so Travis knows what gems should install.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/languages/ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: This is the script to build. In ruby the default script is your rake file, but you can define anything else here —like a shell script which is much more simple. As you see I have a couple of entries here that run depending on the branch it’s pushed.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When I push &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; I run &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.algolia.com/jekyll-algolia/github-pages.html&quot;&gt;Algolia&lt;/a&gt;, build the site and then past the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gjtorikian/html-proofer&quot;&gt;htmlproofer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When I push &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;develop&lt;/code&gt; I just build the site and past the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gjtorikian/html-proofer&quot;&gt;htmlproofer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p class=&quot;notice--warning&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please remember&lt;/strong&gt; to build your site with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;JEKYLL_ENV=production&lt;/code&gt; because if you don’t some features aren’t going to show in the final deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/customizing-the-build/#building-specific-branches&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;branches&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: This define which branches trigger the build. In my case &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;develop&lt;/code&gt;, but you can add/remove whatever you want.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/customizing-the-build/&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;env&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: You can define environment variables and in my case since I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gjtorikian/html-proofer&quot;&gt;htmlproofer&lt;/a&gt; it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/continuous-integration/travis-ci/&quot;&gt;recommended&lt;/a&gt; to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NOKOGIRI_USE_SYSTEM_LIBRARIES&lt;/code&gt; as environment variable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/tutorial/#selecting-infrastructure-optional&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: We don’t need sudo, since we don’t need customizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deploy&quot;&gt;Deploy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the last part of the config file, which is going to deploy the final built product —your website— to your repo again but in a different branch —&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; in my case. Travis &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/deployment/pages/&quot;&gt;has a section&lt;/a&gt; in its documentation about deployment in GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a &lt;em&gt;couple&lt;/em&gt; of notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;on&lt;/code&gt;: States the branch is going to trigger the build it’s the previous test exit with no errors. In other words, only when you push commits to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; Travis is going to deploy your site. If you run Travis in other branches the deployment isn’t going to happen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;target_branch&lt;/code&gt;: This is where is going to be deployed your site. In my case I have a branch only for deployments &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; which I don’t even have locally. Be aware that Travis push with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--force&lt;/code&gt; to that branch so it’s going to overwrite the history in that branch leaving just one commit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;repo&lt;/code&gt;: You can deploy in a different repo if you want, just define username and name of the repo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;local_dir&lt;/code&gt;: Folder from the build that is needed to be deployed, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; in my case.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;keep-history&lt;/code&gt;: If you don’t want Travis to push with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--force&lt;/code&gt; you can set this option to true and it’ll will keep the history of your branch.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;github-token&lt;/code&gt;: You need to provide Travis with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/creating-a-personal-access-token-for-the-command-line/&quot;&gt;GitHub personal access token&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;public_repo&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;repo&lt;/code&gt; scope, depending if you repo is public or private. This token should be private and the best way use it is to configure it in your &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/environment-variables#defining-variables-in-repository-settings&quot;&gt;repository settings&lt;/a&gt; in Travis. If you don’t provide the token correctly, Travis isn’t going to be able to deploy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;skip-cleanup&lt;/code&gt;: You need to set this up as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; if you don’t want Travis to delete everything after it finish the built, which wind up deploying nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;provider&lt;/code&gt;: pages since you are deploying to GitHub Pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you are wondering why perform the building in your different branches and so. Well, have three permanent branches: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;develop&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;writing&lt;/code&gt;. I usually work on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;develop&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;writing&lt;/code&gt; and then I merge to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;. I also use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/comparing-workflows/gitflow-workflow&quot;&gt;Git flow&lt;/a&gt; for making changes in the source code of the site, and I’m thinking to try to implement it also for writing post and pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, I think it’s a good idea to test that everything add up before I merge to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; when I’m working on features. Writing, it’s much more simple, and usually the errors are just that some link isn’t correctly set, which is easy to fix. I sometimes use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gjtorikian/html-proofer&quot;&gt;htmlproofer&lt;/a&gt; locally when I’m writing so I know everything is OK before I merge to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lfs&quot;&gt;LFS?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this moment, I have my configuration exactly like you can see above. However, while I was writing this post, I just discovered that you can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/customizing-the-build#git-lfs&quot;&gt;LFS with Travis&lt;/a&gt; —of course you can, why wouldn’t you? You &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/git-lfs/git-lfs/issues/791#issuecomment-151318020&quot;&gt;can’t use LFS with GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; though, but I wonder if you implement the build of your site with Travis while using LFS, you’ll make it possible. Anyhow, you need to take into account the &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/about-storage-and-bandwidth-usage/&quot;&gt;bandwidth limitations of LFS&lt;/a&gt; and it’s probably that, every time you build with Travis you’ll use part of your bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll try to write a post in the near future about &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-lfs.github.com&quot;&gt;what is LFS (Large File Storage)&lt;/a&gt;, but summing it up a lot, it’s just a system that allow you to manage better large binary files with Git, storing them in alternative storage instead of just tracking them with Git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;These scripts can be whatever you want —more or less. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;IIRC to trigger Travis you also need to have a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; of your repo but I’m not sure. Anyhow… sometimes I have repos in GitHub that have files &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; and I don’t want they run in CI. In the end you can do whatever you think it’s more convenient for you. I don’t think it’s wise to try to build every time you are pushing to your repo and then receive an email of &lt;em&gt;your build is failing!&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/26/how-i-publish-my-blog-ci/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;How I publish my blog: Using Continuous Integration with Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="jekyll" />
      
        <category term="blogging" />
      
        <category term="CI" />
      
        <category term="travis" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As I’ve mentioned before, this blog is build as a static website with Jekyll, which allow me not to worry about data bases, logins or anything of the sorts when I’m publishing and managing the web. I use the free tier of GitHub Pages as hosting, which has its downsides and upsides. The main upside is, it’s really convenient and free. On the other hand, I’m limited to certain Jekyll plugins if I want to use GitHub Pages building capabilities. This can be circumnavigate if you use CI (Continuous Integration) to build your site.</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/jekyll+travis.png" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Cleaning a GeoPackage after merging</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/24/cleaning-geopackage-after-merging/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cleaning a GeoPackage after merging" />
      <published>2018-11-24T19:10:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2018-11-24T19:10:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/24/cleaning-geopackage-after-merging</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/24/cleaning-geopackage-after-merging/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/finnish-forest-stands.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        

        &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/11/19/merging-geopackages/&quot;&gt;other day&lt;/a&gt; I was talking about how you can merge several GeoPackages files in a single GeoPackage —just because you wanted or needed that way. Problem is, sometimes some of the data or information that those GeoPackages contain could be redundan. In my particular case, some information was redundan because the GeoPackages contain forest data at stand level that is also at &lt;a href=&quot;http://kartat.kapsi.fi/files/karttalehtijako_ruudukko/kaikki/etrs89&quot;&gt;UTM10 Finnish’s grid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; level. Since life is imperfect, some stands are between two grid quadrants, so a decision&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; was made to have them in both —or more&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;— of the quadrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we needed to remove those duplicated stand, among other things to leave the GeoPackage ready to be analyzed in R. Most of the scripts we used are in the GeoProcessing tools from the Vector menu in &lt;a href=&quot;https://qgis.org/&quot;&gt;QGIS3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/6V5TRDH.png&quot; title=&quot;GeoProcessing Tools in QGIS3
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/6V5TRDH.png&quot; alt=&quot;GeoProcessing Tools in GIS3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      GeoProcessing Tools in QGIS3

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;removing-the-duplicated-stands&quot;&gt;Removing the duplicated stands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, we need to remove the duplicate stands from our data. This can be performed with the  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dissolve&lt;/code&gt; script where the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;standid&lt;/code&gt; was used as a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Unique ID field&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/jxcQy3h.png&quot; title=&quot;Dissolve script in QGIS3
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/jxcQy3h.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dissolve script in QGIS3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Dissolve script in QGIS3

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;removing-the-stands-outside-of-our-area-of-interest&quot;&gt;Removing the stands outside of our area of interest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-left&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 300px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/e0Hr0H3.png&quot; title=&quot;Stands overflowing the border
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/e0Hr0H3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stands overflowing the border&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Stands overflowing the border

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I told you, there are stands that overflow the grid representing our area of interest. In the previous step we just removed the duplicated stands, but the stands in the outside border of the area of interest weren’t duplicated but part of them were outside, as you can see in the left image. Since we just want the forest area inside of the grid we have to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;clip&lt;/code&gt; those stands using the grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/cgrzUM2.png&quot; title=&quot;Clip script in QGIS3
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/cgrzUM2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clip script in QGIS3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Clip script in QGIS3

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we have a perfect straight borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intersecting-the-stands-and-the-grid&quot;&gt;Intersecting the stands and the grid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we’ve removed the duplicated and overflown, we want to cut the stands by the grid. We are going to to perform our analysis taking the grid’s quadrants as main units, so we need to cut the stands totally straight everywhere not just in the exterior border. In other words, we need to divide the stands that intersect with the gird lines. To make that possible we are going to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;intersection&lt;/code&gt; script&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/G3xocP2.png&quot; title=&quot;Intersection script in QGIS3
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/G3xocP2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Intersection script in QGIS3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Intersection script in QGIS3

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the intersection was performed, the resulting layer is going to have the information from both intersected layers. In other words, each of the stands have a column now where is stated to witch quadrant of the grid belongs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updating-the-area&quot;&gt;Updating the Area&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the intersection with the the grid the areas of the border stands needed to be updated, they aren’t the same any longer since they’ve been divided. To do so we can use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.qgis.org/2.8/en/docs/user_manual/working_with_vector/field_calculator.html&quot;&gt;QGIS field calculator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/5r53J5o.png&quot; title=&quot;Field Calculator in QGIS3
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/5r53J5o.png&quot; alt=&quot;Field Calculator in QGIS3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Field Calculator in QGIS3

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We created a new field and used the formula &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;area($geometry)/10000&lt;/code&gt; to fill it and divided the result by 10000 to get the result in hectares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can know more about this functions from the QGIS3 help. For the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;area&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;function area&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Returns the area of a geometry polygon object. Calculations are always planimetric in the Spatial Reference System (SRS) of this geometry, and the units of the returned area will match the units for the SRS. This differs from the calculations performed by the $area function, which will perform ellipsoidal calculations based on the project’s ellipsoid and area unit settings.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Syntax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;area(geometry)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arguments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;geometry&lt;/em&gt;
polygon geometry object&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;area(geom_from_wkt(‘POLYGON((0 0, 4 0, 4 2, 0 2, 0 0))’)) → 8.0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$geometry&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;function $geometry&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Returns the geometry of the current feature. Can be used for processing with other functions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Syntax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;$geometry&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;geomToWKT( $geometry ) → POINT(6 50)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;layer-housekeeping&quot;&gt;Layer &lt;em&gt;housekeeping&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/T8Yix3U.png&quot; title=&quot;Refactor Fields script in QGIS3
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/T8Yix3U.png&quot; alt=&quot;Refactor Fields script in QGIS3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Refactor Fields script in QGIS3

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the intersection and the creation of the updated area field, a little bit of &lt;em&gt;housekeeping&lt;/em&gt; was needed —in my opinion— in the final layer. It’s always good to keep layers tidy and with just the information you need. Too much information that you don’t need just create clutter, which make difficult to read the useful info. To tidy up the layer we used the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Refractors fields&lt;/code&gt; script on the QGIS &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Vector Layer&lt;/code&gt; toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adjoining-tables&quot;&gt;Adjoining tables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these GeoPackages there are additional info that it’s contained in the adjoined tables. Some of that info it’s going to be also duplicated, but you can’t —or at least I don’t know how— clean that duplicated info in QGIS3. I couldn’t find any script to remove duplicate entries in a table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these info it’s going to be used in R to perform analysis, so it’s probably must more easier to clean those tables there with something like &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/13967063/remove-duplicated-rows&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. This leads us the last step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;linking-and-using-the-geopackages-in-r&quot;&gt;Linking and using the GeoPackages in R&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the last step, but to know more about this you can check &lt;a href=&quot;https://olalladiaz.net/blog/2018/11/02/working-with-gpkg-r/&quot;&gt;Olalla’s post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A little bit more of info about the Finnish grid can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maanmittauslaitos.fi/asioi-verkossa/palveluiden-kayttoohjeet/kiinteistotietopalvelun-kayttoohjeet/kartan-haku#haku-karttalehden-numerolla&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; 🇫🇮. Basically the grid numbers refer to the scale of the sheet, so UTM10 mean the sheets are in 1:10000 scale. This comes from the era when papers maps were the only thing available so the country has to be gridded in some way. Usually these sheets are just subdivisions of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_Transverse_Mercator_coordinate_system&quot;&gt;Universal Transverse Mercator coordinate system&lt;/a&gt;. The scale also mean how detailed is the cartography inside of the sheet. So in this case your cartography is 1:10000 detailed. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I don’t know if the decision was good of bad, but I guess it was the best —and a &lt;em&gt;middle road&lt;/em&gt;— solution. In the end, the criteria to include a stand in one or another quadrant could come off being really fuzzy. It was probably munch easier to select all the features &lt;em&gt;contained within&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;intersecting with&lt;/em&gt; each of the grid’s quadrants. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I imagine that chances are some stands are in up to four quadrants at the same time, if they are in one of the corners or intersections of the grid. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/24/cleaning-geopackage-after-merging/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Cleaning a GeoPackage after merging&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="Finland" />
      
        <category term="forest inventory" />
      
        <category term="data science" />
      
        <category term="QGIS" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The other day I was talking about how you can merge several GeoPackages files in a single GeoPackage —just because you wanted or needed that way. Problem is, sometimes some of the data or information that those GeoPackages contain could be redundan. In my particular case, some information was redundan because the GeoPackages contain forest data at stand level that is also at UTM10 Finnish’s grid1 level. Since life is imperfect, some stands are between two grid quadrants, so a decision2 was made to have them in both —or more3— of the quadrants. A little bit more of info about the Finnish grid can be found here 🇫🇮. Basically the grid numbers refer to the scale of the sheet, so UTM10 mean the sheets are in 1:10000 scale. This comes from the era when papers maps were the only thing available so the country has to be gridded in some way. Usually these sheets are just subdivisions of the Universal Transverse Mercator coordinate system. The scale also mean how detailed is the cartography inside of the sheet. So in this case your cartography is 1:10000 detailed. &amp;#8617; I don’t know if the decision was good of bad, but I guess it was the best —and a middle road— solution. In the end, the criteria to include a stand in one or another quadrant could come off being really fuzzy. It was probably munch easier to select all the features contained within and intersecting with each of the grid’s quadrants. &amp;#8617; I imagine that chances are some stands are in up to four quadrants at the same time, if they are in one of the corners or intersections of the grid. &amp;#8617;</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/finnish-forest-stands.png" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Trump, raking, Finland &amp;amp; wildfires</title>
      <link href="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/23/trump-raking-finland-and-wildfires/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trump, raking, Finland &amp; wildfires" />
      <published>2018-11-23T10:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2018-11-23T11:35:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/23/trump-raking-finland-and-wildfires</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/23/trump-raking-finland-and-wildfires/">
        
        
          
          
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/raking-forest.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        

        
          
          &lt;figure class=&quot; &quot;&gt;
  
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
        

        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update Sunday 25th Nov 2018 at 11.35 UTC:&lt;/strong&gt; Just to clarify a little bit. &lt;strong&gt;What we really need is more management, not less.&lt;/strong&gt; We need to get the most of our forest, while conserving them and try to understand better how to the natural system that it’s works. We can’t abandon our forest to their luck &lt;em&gt;in the wild&lt;/em&gt; now because it would be like abandoning our dog in the forest just because &lt;em&gt;it’s an animal and it should know how to survive&lt;/em&gt;. Probably it won’t. We also need to assume that, as animals, we are part of the ecosystem and we need to play a role too. What we really need to figure out is what is our role. I assure you that, as any other animal out there, our role isn’t going to be a passive one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL:NR:&lt;/strong&gt; This post was in the beginning much sorter, but sometimes ideas have life in their own. I’m sorry to not be able to be more concise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since people has been talking about this non-stop, I’m a forester, I live in Finland and I’ve been in the US, lets have a post about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you probably already know, this year has been a really nasty wildfire season in US and recently a really devastating wildfire occurred, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camp_Fire_(2018)&quot;&gt;Camp Fire&lt;/a&gt;, which has left a incredible track of destruction, desolation and pain on the population that suffered its effects. President Trump decided to pay a visit to the place of the devastation and he decided to make this statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nwL6GWYg34M&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… first of all, I really don’t understand why this man don’t take the opportunity to just being silent or at the very least, don’t talk about something he —clearly— doesn’t have an idea how it works. This phrase sparked a myriad of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/11/12/us/politics/fact-check-trump-california-fire-tweet.html&quot;&gt;responses&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/trump-tweet-about-california-fires-firefighter-union-president-responds-for-what-president-said-about-california-wildfires/&quot;&gt;critiques&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arktimes.com/ArkansasBlog/archives/2018/11/18/trump-calls-for-raking-to-prevent-fires-claims-its-the-finnish-way-fake-news-anyone&quot;&gt;mockery&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/world/2018/11/19/18102613/finland-trump-raking-woods&quot;&gt;memes&lt;/a&gt; in US, in Finland and all over the World. News outlets even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/story/2018/11/18/trump-raking-wildfires-california-finland-1002526&quot;&gt;asked the president of Finland&lt;/a&gt; if he and Trump were talking about raking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that statement, he also decided to tweet —oh no … here we go— another statement related to “forest management”, on which of course he is an expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;There is no reason for these massive, deadly and costly forest fires in California except that forest management is so poor. Billions of dollars are given each year, with so many lives lost, all because of gross mismanagement of the forests. Remedy now, or no more Fed payments!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Donald J. Trump (@realDonaldTrump) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/1061168803218948096?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;November 10, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s try to respond, with a little bit of rational thinking, to this non-sense. Please, bear also in mind that although I’m a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forestry&quot;&gt;Forest Engineer&lt;/a&gt;, and I do have formal education in wildfires&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I’m not, by no means, an expert in the topic. I know the basics, how wildfires usually spread, how to manage fighting operations and, of course, how to manage the forest to decrease the risk of wildfire happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-finns-rake-their-forest&quot;&gt;Do Finns rake their forest?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really don’t know what Trump and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sauli_Niinistö&quot;&gt;Niinistö&lt;/a&gt; were talking about, but I hope, I really hope, they weren’t talking about &lt;em&gt;raking the forest floors&lt;/em&gt; and they were spending they time in more productive topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NO!!!&lt;/strong&gt; Finns, and no-one else, rake the forest floors… they don’t even rake the leaves on the street where we live since they use leaf blowers to keep the street clean&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-left&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 300px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/mcleod.jpg&quot; title=&quot;McLeod Rake
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/mcleod.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;McLeod Rake&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McLeod_%28tool%29&quot;&gt;McLeod Rake&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it’s true that Finns take care of their forest with great dedication since they’re an important part of Finnish economy and culture, they are the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.metla.fi/metinfo/sustainability/finnish.htm&quot;&gt;most forested country in Europe&lt;/a&gt;. Normal logging operations are carried out and, of course, maintenance operations as: thinnings, clearings, extractions, afforestations, reforestations, etc. You have to bear in mind that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.metla.fi/metinfo/sustainability/finnish.htm&quot;&gt;majority of Finnish forest (96%)&lt;/a&gt;, is classified as semi-natural forest, in other words they are managed or have been managed at some point in their history. Around 60% of the forest is owned by private individuals and the 9% by forest companies, so around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forestindustries.fi/statistics/forest-resources-and-wood-raw-material/&quot;&gt;70% of the Finnish forest is private&lt;/a&gt;, while 26% is owned by the state. In other words, most of the forest in Finland is productive forest &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.metla.fi/metinfo/sustainability/finnish-non-wood.htm&quot;&gt;for wood&lt;/a&gt; and usually forest companies, forest associations or private individuals take care of &lt;em&gt;their piece of the forest&lt;/em&gt; in one way or another and with or without the help of the state. Unless the forest is under some sort of protection, dead trees and wood are usually extracted and the amount of fuel is kept as low as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, there are some people that really rake the forest with a forest rake, but I doubt they can be found in Finland. The forest rake is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McLeod_%28tool%29&quot;&gt;McLeod&lt;/a&gt; and it’s sometimes use by fire combatants&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to create defensive lines agains wildfires. They remove debris and vegetation and create a stripe of mineral soil where the fire can be stopped by lowering its intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-california--us-forest-comparable-to-finnish-forest&quot;&gt;Is California / US forest comparable to Finnish forest?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, although they share for sure some characteristics and I’m not an expert in Californian forest, they are pretty different. The US Pacific Northwest is closer to the Finnish forest, thought. But you have to keep in mind that most of Finnish forest, if not all, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taiga#/media/File:Distribution_Taiga.png&quot;&gt;is boreal forest&lt;/a&gt; while not even the Pacific Northwest forest hold this biome. This make these forest hardly comparable. You have to think Finnish forest is composed mostly by &lt;strong&gt;3 tree species&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; while American / Californian forest have &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_California_native_plants#Selected_trees&quot;&gt;dozes of different tree species&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting difference is orography. While California has a vast &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geography_of_California&quot;&gt;diversity of terrains and orography&lt;/a&gt;, Finland is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geography_of_Finland&quot;&gt;mainly flat&lt;/a&gt; —like a board. Of course, Finland possesses some &lt;em&gt;hilly&lt;/em&gt; features, mostly located in the North, but nothing comparable to the mountainous terrain you can find in California, and more specific where this tragedy happened, in the lower parts of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sierra_Nevada_(U.S.)&quot;&gt;Sierra Nevada&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, but not less important, is the climate. While California has around &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_of_California&quot;&gt;10 different climates&lt;/a&gt;, being the most commons the mediterranean&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the desert ones. Meanwhile, Finland has —again— &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_of_Finland&quot;&gt;3 different kinds of climates&lt;/a&gt;, being the vastly most common the subarctic. This is of extreme importance because most of the year the Finnish forest is wet —either under the snow or really moisturized. That doesn’t mean that there isn’t a wildfire risk in Finland, just that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taiga#Fire&quot;&gt;fire regime is different&lt;/a&gt;. If the conditions are met, wildfire risk increase, and sadly and due climate change, the conditions are met more often each year&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. However, this doesn’t mean that wildfires will happen, even more if you follow a correct prevention forest management and you try to reduce the fuel in the forest as much as possible as they seem to been doing in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/2018/11/19/why-finland-is-so-good-handling-forest-fires-hint-its-not-because-raking/?noredirect=on&amp;amp;utm_term=.7aa35a63b520&quot;&gt;Finland using prescribed fire&lt;/a&gt;. These bring us to the next question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;has-there-been-poor-management&quot;&gt;Has there been poor management?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wildfire-fighting&quot;&gt;Wildfire fighting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really difficult to say and even more when you don’t have all the data, and I don’t —and I won’t— have it, and really few people will. The wildfire is right now under investigation and they are even still fighting it. I really doubt that there is anyone really responsible for it and/or the casualties, and I also doubt that blame would be the answer. I just can give all my support to the victims and of course all the combatants. Wildfires are really really complicated beast and even more when they reach certain size, as this one has been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forest-management&quot;&gt;Forest management&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, again, I’m not an expert on what kind of management have been applied in Californian forest and I don’t really know anything in detail about it. However, we can draw some facts here that will probably help us to understand a little bit better the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;those-arent-forest-fires&quot;&gt;Those aren’t forest fires&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, those &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wildfire&quot;&gt;wildfires&lt;/a&gt; aren’t exactly forest fires. As this piece in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/11/12/us/politics/fact-check-trump-california-fire-tweet.html&quot;&gt;The New York Times points out&lt;/a&gt;, the fire has cause such an incredible damage, lost of life and properties basically because it run over a &lt;em&gt;wildland-urban interface: places where communities are close to undeveloped areas, making it easier for fire to move from forests or grasslands into neighborhoods&lt;/em&gt;. To put in another way, fire spread over places where people live in really close contact with forest and nature. You can check &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@39.8073851,-121.4371413,66676m/data=!3m1!1e3!4m3!15m2!1m1!1s%2Fg%2F11fhnfzqjf?hl=en&quot;&gt;Google Maps aerial photo&lt;/a&gt;, or better yet, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=5306cc8cf38c4252830a38d467d33728&amp;amp;extent=-13547810.5486%2C4824920.1673%2C-13518764.4778%2C4841526.1117%2C102100&quot;&gt;Camp Fire’s Structure Status, from California Department of Forestry and Fire Protection&lt;/a&gt;, to get an idea of how destructive the fire has been and how was the structure of the landscape was burned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pge&quot;&gt;PG&amp;amp;E&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the investigation is still ongoing and we don’t know anything for sure yet, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfgate.com/california-wildfires/article/cause-butte-county-california-wildfire-source-13395622.php&quot;&gt;some people&lt;/a&gt; —they even have begun a lawsuit— have pointed fingers to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Gas_and_Electric_Company&quot;&gt;Pacific Gas and Electric Company&lt;/a&gt; as the possible responsible of the ignition of the fire. We can read in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camp_Fire_(2018)#Timeline&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The fire started at sunrise on Thursday, November 8, 2018, and was first reported at 6:33 a.m. PST, near &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulga,_California&quot;&gt;Pulga, California&lt;/a&gt;, near Camp Creek Road in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butte_County,_California&quot;&gt;Butte County&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California&quot;&gt;California&lt;/a&gt;. Soon after the ignition of the Camp Fire, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glossary_of_wildfire_terms#I&quot;&gt;initial attack&lt;/a&gt; firefighters were dispatched to a report of a brush fire under &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Gas_and_Electric_Company&quot;&gt;Pacific Gas and Electric Company&lt;/a&gt; (PG&amp;amp;E) power lines near &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poe_Dam&quot;&gt;Poe Dam&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feather_River&quot;&gt;Feather River&lt;/a&gt;. Arriving 10 minutes later, the first units on scene observed rapid fire growth and extreme fire behavior due to low humidity and high winds in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the approximate location of the fire ignition &lt;a href=&quot;https://arcg.is/0ajH0K&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, this seems that it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/12-Northern-California-fires-caused-by-PG-E-power-12979955.php&quot;&gt;isn’t the first time PG&amp;amp;E equipment has been found as the responsible of igniting a forest fire&lt;/a&gt; although they are trying to distance themselves from the events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power lines have to be really clean and they are usually cleared every year to minimize the risk of fire. Trees are also checked so no branches are in danger to touch the line and crease a spark, a fire and a power outage. However, all of this is costly and require a lot of time, and humans, to review and clean those power lines stripes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cal-fire&quot;&gt;Cal Fire&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;US sometimes is really messy when it comes to who has to do what and who is the responsible to this and that. Some times responsibilities fall under the Federal Government and sometimes under the State Governments and sometimes under both and other times no one knows what is going on… Don’t be surprised because this is the &lt;em&gt;bread and butter&lt;/em&gt; of almost any federal state / country —Spain is almost a federal state and we have this problems too— even more if it’s old —in Spain boundaries of forest, municipalities, properties, regions, etc are so messy that I have a headache only to remember it— and even more if the state is big —EU is as big, or more, than US, and its becoming to have this kind of issues too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cal Fire (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fire.ca.gov&quot;&gt;The Department of Forestry and Fire Protection&lt;/a&gt;) seems to be the responsible for the forest management in California. But they seems to be mainly focused in Fire Fighting, representing more than the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebudget.ca.gov/2016-17/StateAgencyBudgets/3000/3540/department.html&quot;&gt;80% of the agency budget&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://sacramento.cbslocal.com/2018/09/09/cal-fire-budget/&quot;&gt;is not even close to be enough&lt;/a&gt; to maintain this wildfire regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, we have to take into account that &lt;a href=&quot;https://arcg.is/0S9uvu&quot;&gt;the fire started inside the limits&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plumas_National_Forest&quot;&gt;Plumas National Forest&lt;/a&gt; which is under the jurisdiction of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fs.usda.gov/plumas/&quot;&gt;US Forest Service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;us-forest-service&quot;&gt;US Forest Service&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-right&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 300px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0f/Smokey_Bear_Only_You_campaign_hat.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Smokey the Bear
&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0f/Smokey_Bear_Only_You_campaign_hat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smokey_Bear&quot;&gt;Smokey the Bear&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US Forest Service has a really &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_wildfire_suppression_in_the_United_States&quot;&gt;long tradition of fighting wildfires&lt;/a&gt; and I would say that most of the wildfire science and techniques has been developed by this US Government agency. They are also probably the organization that most forest science produces in the World&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; including wildfire management. US citizens should be proud of all the people working at the agency because they do a really an incredible job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, US Forest service seems that has been in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/docrep/010/ai412e/AI412E06.htm&quot;&gt;decline&lt;/a&gt; in the last decades, with shifts in policy, vision, aims, organization, etc… and without a clear mandate from the government. Traditionally, the US Forest service had an approach to forestry from the natural resource management, but from the 60s on this approach begun to shift to a more conservation vision, and different &lt;em&gt;families&lt;/em&gt; with different approach begun to appear. Society also has changed, and we all are now more worried about environmental issues. All of these have created a more &lt;em&gt;hostile&lt;/em&gt; environment to manage forests, increasing the numbers of stakeholders involved in the decision-making processes for managing. Where there were just the USF Service employees, the communities close and relaying in those forest resources and the timber industry, now there are a plethora of individuals and organization that want —and probably should— to have a say in the managing processes and activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is isn’t something good or bad per se, just it’s, and reflects that, what we demand as society from our natural resources has shifted, but it has increase the time and resources needed to produce the same amount of decisions, plans, solutions and other products. Before, we just needed wood, now need more products, some of them even as intangible as “&lt;em&gt;feeling good because we are taking care of Earth&lt;/em&gt;” or “&lt;em&gt;a beautiful forest&lt;/em&gt;”. I really think that the environmental movement from the 60s and 70s &lt;strong&gt;was really positive&lt;/strong&gt;, meaning for a lot of people the awakening to the idea that we need to take care of our planet. This was probably part as a result of policies from US Forest Service and National Parks Service —among others— that little by little begun to &lt;em&gt;democratize nature&lt;/em&gt; and approach it in a gentle manner in National Parks and National Forest. We in the end begun to think that we need to take care of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, sometimes &lt;em&gt;hell is paved with good intentions&lt;/em&gt; and this has brought us to a &lt;em&gt;gridlock&lt;/em&gt; situation where forest’s health has decrease and fuel has built up. To add up, although the budget of the service has been increased in latter years, all that increase has been assigned to wildfire management — while it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/spiraling-wildfire-fighting-costs-are-largely-beyond-the-forest-services-control-86041&quot;&gt;not even enough&lt;/a&gt;— while the other areas of the service has been stalked and degreasing budget due to inflation, and seems that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.taxpayer.net/energy-natural-resources/proposed-cuts-increased-timber-cutting-forest-service/&quot;&gt;further budgetary&lt;/a&gt; cuts are planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot; style=&quot;font-size: small&quot;&gt;I really recommend to read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/docrep/010/ai412e/AI412E06.htm&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; to have a broader vision about the US Forest Service situation and history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;climate-change&quot;&gt;Climate Change&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people have also been pointing fingers to climate change as a direct cause of the increase and virulence of wildfires. I would say that they are right and they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the existence of Climate Change is something &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalscience.com&quot;&gt;undeniable&lt;/a&gt; and it’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/2018/11/12/meteorologist-california-fire-donald-trump/&quot;&gt;more than probable they play role in increase of wildfires&lt;/a&gt;, it isn’t the only factor in the increase and it shouldn’t be used as an excuse in my opinion. It’s true that the unusual dry and hot conditions, that seems to be driven by climate change, increase the amount of dry and fine fuels in forest and converts it in a tinderbox. However, you have to take into account that there are forest in really diverse climate conditions and places under different management regimes and some of them end up charred and some others don’t. If we look at the below figures, you can see that it’s really interesting that in Spain where most wildfires occur, is where precipitation is higher and the temperatures are milder. It’s also where one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.efi.int/knowledge/maps/forest&quot;&gt;most forested area of Spain is located&lt;/a&gt;, but they are other areas with plenty of forest and they don’t get burned. We also have to take into account that wildfires in Spain have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.efe.com/efe/espana/sociedad/los-grandes-incendios-queman-el-60-de-la-superficie-un-20-mas-media/10004-2682340&quot;&gt;decreased&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third &quot;&gt;
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/wildfires-spain.png&quot; title=&quot;Wildfires in Spain.
&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/wildfires-spain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wildfires in Spain&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/precipitation-spain.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Mean precipitation in Spain.
&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/precipitation-spain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mean precipitation in Spain&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/temperature-spain.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Mean temperature in Spain.
&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2018/temperature-spain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mean temperature in Spain&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wildfire incidence, mean precipitation and mean temperature in Spain. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://picazo.eltiempo.es/los-incendios-queman-menos-espana-este-2016/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ign.es/espmap/mapas_clima_bach.htm&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management here is a key, and also culture. Part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_Spain&quot;&gt;Green Spain&lt;/a&gt; has a culture of using fire to clear forest to create pasture. How forest are managed and how the property and gains are share among local populations also play a role. Most the wildfires in Spain have a human cause, and a lot of them are intentional. Quarrels, bitterness, grievance, resentment, grudge, etc are common causes of a lot of fires. Not to mention &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.farodevigo.es/galicia/2016/08/15/hallan-velas-incendio-declarado-padrenda/1516191.html&quot;&gt;derange people&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;us-congress-the-president--california&quot;&gt;US Congress, The President &amp;amp; California&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Forest Service and Cal Fire, depend directly from US Congress, The President of US and the State of California. Those agencies depend on them for organization, mandate and budget. In other words, although they are, or try to be, fairly independent agencies, government still set the general guidelines and set the budget they can and should spend. They also create and enforce the legislation that those agencies has to follow and enforce. Those agencies are just tools of their respective governments to fulfill the purpose of manage and preserve forest and protect forest and population from wildfires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion was quite clear from the very beginning, one shouldn’t talk about something that doesn’t have a minimum knowledge about an Trump shouldn’t be an exception of that rule of thumb. In the very end, the US Government, from whom he is one of the highest responsible now, is the real responsible. Is he going to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=75SEy1qu71I&quot;&gt;fire himself&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What he should be doing is to try to increase the budget to fight forest fires and start the preparations for restore the area. And of course, prepare the relief fund for the victims. It’s pretty clear to me that &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcnews.go.com/US/trump-threatens-pull-federal-funding-california-wildfires-gross/story?id=59102371&quot;&gt;decrease funding isn’t the way to go&lt;/a&gt;. US Forest Service, Cal Fire, and all the rest of the agencies involved in managing natural resources —in the US and in the rest of the World— have ahead the titanic task of managing those resources in a world threatened, and in constant change, as a consequence of Climate Change. Those are vital for the future of Humanity and need to figure out the best and most efficient way to manage them to still enjoy them while keeping them safe. We are going to need more funds and personnel than ever to fulfill that task and we need to switch from a strategy of just defending those resources from hazards to a more efficient policy—not only &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2015/08/19/what-the-wildfires-are-costing-us.html&quot;&gt;economically&lt;/a&gt; but in all other terms— of preventing those hazards. Sometimes, hazards can’t be predicted and the worst can —and perhaps should— happen, so we also need to work to make those resources —and the communities living and relying on them— as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_swan_theory&quot;&gt;resilient as possible&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a society, we also need to rethink our approach to natural resources and what we really want to demand from them and from the agencies in charge of taking care of them. Sometimes I wonder if the &lt;em&gt;democratization of nature&lt;/em&gt; has been positive. On one had, I really appreciate the interest of the people on taking care of our blue planet and this interest and concern in really needed to demand policies that change things and help to preserve those resource. On the other hand, we end many times in gridlock situations that last forever and in clashes of interest that many times are driven by misconceptions of what nature really is and should be manage. Neither is just a resource that should be sold and use for profit, nor is that idilic place that fairy tales have build in our head and where everything is perfect and set in place for our enjoyment and aesthetic reasons. We have to understand also that perhaps sometimes nature works in a quite &lt;a href=&quot;https://eu.usatoday.com/story/news/2018/08/08/california-fires-battling-wildfires-year-round-new-normal/930394002/&quot;&gt;counterintuitive way&lt;/a&gt; and that we should adapt our policies and mindsets to our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/morning-mix/wp/2018/08/15/was-smokey-bear-wrong-how-a-beloved-character-may-have-helped-fuel-catastrophic-fires/?utm_term=.4830775b10bd&quot;&gt;current understanding of the ecosystems&lt;/a&gt;. Nature isn’t always pretty or nice, and beauty is really &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-O5kNPlUV7w&quot;&gt;a human concept&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, natural resources should be, and need to be, used with respect. The best way to preserve something is to use it with care and respect. Putting them into a glass urn for our enjoyment is just going to make things worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In my studies in Spain, where fighting wildfires are an important part of being a forester, even more in my region where have the highest density of wildfires in Spain, I took a couple of courses about &lt;em&gt;defending the forest&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;fighting wildfires&lt;/em&gt;. After that, I took also a couple of curses in the topic, with one being a &lt;em&gt;Fire Management&lt;/em&gt; Course in the North of Sweden. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes, municipalities and building owners pay someone to take care of this problem, in the same way someone comes to clean the snow of the street and your building door. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I say &lt;em&gt;sometimes&lt;/em&gt; because, as you can read in the Wikipedia, it’s a quite awkward tool to transport and to deal with. I think I’ve only seen one once and most of the forestry people doesn’t even know that this tool exist. In other words, it’s quite rare. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Scotch pine (&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scots_pine&quot;&gt;Pinus sylvestris&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;), spruce (&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Picea_abies&quot;&gt;Picea abies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;) and birch (&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birch&quot;&gt;Betula sp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; although mostly &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betula_pendula&quot;&gt;Betula pendula&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s quite funny because California it’s one of the few places in the World outside of the Mediterranean basic with a Mediterranean Climate &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Those conditions are hotter and drier summers. You have to think that the floor of the boreal forest is composed mainly by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plant_litter&quot;&gt;fine debris and litter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lichen&quot;&gt;lichens&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moss&quot;&gt;mosses&lt;/a&gt;. All those elements are quite vulnerable to dry out under high temperatures and become a high flammable fuel. However, this temperatures has to continue for a while to really transform the forest into a tinderbox. I remember when I was taking my Fire Management course in the North of Sweden that we have programmed a practical exercise where we have to burn a really small portion —probably less than 10x10 meters— of the forest. We have to really wait, and be on call from the instructors, to be able finally perform the exercise because the weather was so humid —it wasn’t even raining— that the forest ground was really wet and not even using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Driptorch&quot;&gt;driptorches&lt;/a&gt; was possible to start the fire. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Which is normal, if you take into account that is probably the forest organization with the biggest budget and with the biggest number of employees. They take care of almost the half of the forest of North America, so they can easily produce that quantity of science, which is really nice. I hope that we can create something similar in the EU. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://luispuerto.net/blog/2018/11/23/trump-raking-finland-and-wildfires/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Trump, raking, Finland &amp;amp; wildfires&lt;/a&gt; was originally published on Luis Puerto’s Blog.&lt;/p&gt;

      </content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Luis Puerto</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="Finland" />
      
        <category term="wildfires" />
      
        <category term="forest management" />
      
        <category term="USA" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Update Sunday 25th Nov 2018 at 11.35 UTC: Just to clarify a little bit. What we really need is more management, not less. We need to get the most of our forest, while conserving them and try to understand better how to the natural system that it’s works. We can’t abandon our forest to their luck in the wild now because it would be like abandoning our dog in the forest just because it’s an animal and it should know how to survive. Probably it won’t. We also need to assume that, as animals, we are part of the ecosystem and we need to play a role too. What we really need to figure out is what is our role. I assure you that, as any other animal out there, our role isn’t going to be a passive one.</summary>
      

      
        
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://luispuerto.net/assets/images/blog/2018/raking-forest.jpg" />
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>